the science and practice of enhancing
human performance for sport play and
life Welcome to
perform I'm Dr Andy Galpin I'm a
professor and scientist and the
executive director of the human
performance center at Parker University
today's guest is Dr Brett conteras Brett
has a PHD in sports science a master's
degree in exercise science and is a
certified strength and conditioning
coach Brett is known popularly as the
glute guy and that's because he spent
the last 30 years of his career focusing
on the science and application of
maximizing muscle growth and strength
development in the lower body and
specifically the glute or butt muscles
we'll talk about that a lot today you'll
learn a tremendous amount about how to
optimize training for the glutes but
we'll talk about much more than that
you're going to learn a lot about
Anatomy physiology biome mechanics and
other things as they apply to practical
recommendations Brett does a phenomenal
job and has over his career of weaving
these things into conversations not so
that you learn unneeded or unnecessary
mathematic principles but so that you
can really maximize your understanding
of why certain exercises do certain
things and others do not this is going
to allow you to leave this conversation
whether you're coaching people or just
here for your own personal needs having
a much better understanding of how to
choose the exact right exercise based
upon what you're trying to get and what
you're not trying to get so Brett has
spent a lot of career on people who are
training that want specific spefic
development in a particular part of the
lower body and not in others you'll
learn a lot about how to do that you'll
also learn about how to make sure that
that exercise is doing the right thing
for you personally that you're wanting
it to do so you're going to have a lot
of fun you'll take a lot away from this
I hope you can extend these learnings
again from just females to men as well
from just the lower body to the upper
body as well and so overall you can
enhance the Precision accuracy and
effectiveness of your training and
fitness routines specifically regarding
developing strength and muscle size and
the lower body that all said please
enjoy my conversation today with Dr Bret
contras Dr Bret contras thank you so
much for being here thank you for having
me the world knows you for the most part
as the glute guy and we will certainly
talk about the glutes today but I know
you as the guy who used to write
extensive articles on the science of
strength training mechanics I don't know
how many of those things you wrote and I
read many years ago before social media
existed but it's very funny for me to
hear people talk about you and and then
my perception of you is like this is the
Science Guy this is not the glute Guy
this is the deep passionate love for
science guys so I don't know where our
conversation is going to go today but I
certainly know we will definitely talk
about the glutes and how to train and
why and all those things like that but
I'm personally a little bit more
interested in kind of the other science
stuff so um that is a little bit of my
lead in I don't I don't know how you
view all that stuff but that's my
perception of of Dr breas appreciate
that to to get us started we're gonna
play the hits right we'll talk about the
glutes and all that um but what I was
really hoping to go into very first is
you made a a post fairly recently that I
thought was really insightful and
actually I've changed how I do stuff now
permanently because of a single post
that you made and that was referring to
the difference in how to train women
versus men now my answer which I've
changed my tune on typically is because
I've trained a lot of female athletes is
there's not that many things that are
different but you actually gave some
incredible insights into things that are
different and and how you do differently
and someone who's trained I don't know
80% of your clients over your career
been female more I don't know what's a
fair number there probably 90 90 plus
percent um what are off the top of your
head some of the the major differences
uh in coaching females and I'll give you
context for you we're talking about
strength training or strength training
related activities not endurance running
and like all things like that so kind of
within this willhouse um how do you
think about this it's just mainly their
goals and so men can't seem to wrap
their head around it like it's funny
you're saying because this was literally
me yeah it's most men um because we want
hypertrophy everywhere if you were like
hey Andy you mind if I slap a little
muscle on your traps you'd be like I'll
take it each delt head sure buys tries
sure pecs upper lower yeah you can't
name a muscle right now that I'm not
going to say yes to say yes to
everything we want to grow everything
and so therefore when we do our leg days
with squats and deadlifts and lunges and
um that that tends to grow a lot of quad
and adct and glutes but here's the
here's the deal a lot of women if they
lean out if they get lean they like the
way they look they might want a little
bit more quad and that not too much but
they want a lot more glute it's that's
the goal is to have large glutes in fact
now surgeries are becoming very common
because of that because it's hard to get
glutes through training uh through even
through proper training some don't get
the glute mask they desire so women want
glutes okay say a man wanted arms as bad
as women want glutes we said
look we want you to give you I I say I'm
a man I want the biggest arms possible
you wouldn't say that like you wouldn't
go Andy quit doing isolation lifts um
and just free weights only do the and
just do you know you're going to get big
triceps if you develop a strong bench
right and weighted dips and close grip
bench and you're know going to get big
biceps if you do weighted chinups and
pull Downs supernat pull Downs right
every guy knows that if if I said I will
give you a million bucks if you put 2 in
on your arms in the next 6 months what
would every guy do they'd start training
it at least three days a week you You'
throw what you know out you wouldn't go
oh train a muscle one day a week you'd
say no I'm going to train it at least
care what studies say you might even
Venture into training it every day you
might be like I think I can do some
curls every day and You' you'd use
variety you you but you'd be going I'm
going to get as strongest possible close
grip bench and weighted dips I'm going
to get my weighted China but that's
going to make up you know maybe a third
of your volume 2/3 are going to be curls
and tricep extensions
now now use that exact same uh strategy
for women with the glutes yes they're
going to do the squats they're going to
do their lunges they're going to do
their Romanian deadlifts Bulgarian
step-ups Etc and they're going to try to
get strong at those but if that's all
you did you're leaving a lot on the
table you your maximum recoverable
volume for glutes is probably 36 to 45
sets a week if you split it up properly
and but here's the deal like because if
you said Andy you're only allowed to do
like breathing squats one set to F like
you know like where
you're you know you grind it out you you
can do squat squats to failure deadlifts
to failure and like walking barbell
lunges to complete failure how many sets
could we squeeze in a week and recover
from it still
you know maybe 10 sets a week tops like
where you're too failure especially when
you're not 22 years old and on you know
potentially recovery AIDS it's going to
be tough no peeds yeah and you're not
not not 18 years old anymore okay so
you're going to do that still you're
going to still do your your compound
list but then you think hip thrust if
all you did was barbell hip thrust you
could easily do them every other day you
they don't beat you up much they would
you get short muscle
lanes and people will say well they
don't grow they work you at Short muscle
Lanes they're not as as effective hold
on now we got three studies now we have
the Plotkin
2023 we have ciano 2023 and now we have
Bartholomew 2024 all
indicating that
they're just as effective as stretch
position movements okay so we don't the
jury's out GL for glute growth so the
jury's still out we need more specific
research but um but it it seems like
they're just as effective so if they
don't beat you up as much and you can do
more volume why not add those in the
other thing is it's like delts how much
how much delt volume could you handle
per week it's it's a different thing
when there's different subdivisions like
yes we so every set of bench incline
military dips that you do is front delt
and if you're in the frontal if if
you're in the frontal plane it's it's
side delt too people think military
press if if especially behind the neck
press activates the the lateral delts
very well but and you know technically
every pull down in row you do works the
rear delts but I I know personally I I
grow my rear delts way better when I
perform specific movements for them and
it's like noticeable so anyway yes you
got all your compound this but you they
can you could throw in if all you were
trying to do was grow your delts you
could probably do some
isolation work for all three heads every
other day now with the glutes the like
women want the Shelf they want their
upper glutes too well so there's the
glut medius that's a separate glut
medius and Minimus is a separate muscle
so that volume doesn't that's separate
volume but also there's some evidence
about you know with regards to the upper
and lower glues Maximus we need more
research because the only training study
was Plotkin and it showed the same upper
and lower glute growth bir versus
between vertical and horizontal but we
have some EMG
evidence um like when you put bands
around your knees and do hip thrust uh
tends to activate the upper glute Max
not the glute medius by the way women
will do it for the glut medius and it
doesn't activate the glut medius more it
activates the glut medus less but it
activates the upper glutax more but not
the lower glutax more a lot of we're
lacking a lot of research but my point
is you can you can do a lot of volume if
your main goal is glut so quit thinking
about bro splits quit thinking about you
know a man decided one
day uh look at the human body look at it
imagine on a anatomy chart okay I'm
going to T split this upper half into
five five different days I'm going to
split this lower half into just one day
for everything yeah now you see some
bodybuilders over the years who did do
break their lower body into a quad focus
and a hamstring Focus but bodybuilders
body building is not about male
bodybuilding is not about glute
development now and so most of the male
bodybuilders they don't they just if you
do steroids and train your legs you end
up with fine glute development and then
it's about getting shredded glutes
that's diet and conditioning so they
don't train for maximum glute
hypertrophy if they did they would have
separate glute days and so they don't
care about that the women care about
that and then male some men care about
maximizing glute size like me guy who
never had any glutes that's why I became
the glute guy I had to study my butt off
to grow to grow them cuz I'm like I'm
doing these exercis I don't feel them
working my glutes as as you know as well
as I
should so that's the main difference
with women they want glute development
is their number one goal so they're
going to train glutes three days a week
most of them okay you threw out so much
gold right there uh we're going to take
a very long time unwinding and packing a
lot of the things you put there's a lot
of terminology in there that I followed
along with it probably missed some
people though I want to make sure
everything you just said people can
grasp how helpful and important that was
so we're probably going to spend a large
chunk of the next few minutes here going
back through some of those things but to
summarize the the initial question again
the context I laid out for you was women
this is the strength training side of
the equation this isn't Mobility this
isn't necessarily body composition or
fat loss or endurance this is simply if
women want to lift weights and men want
to lift weights what are some of the
things we should think about that
differentiates them and the case you
made pretty eloquently there is often
times certainly not every real quick
this is important I want to give some
shout out some credit you you you said
this is about this is about hypertrophy
mainly like this isn't about athleticism
but I wouldn't never came up with these
methods that I've popularized if it
weren't for my strength coaching
background we're going to get into that
here right now submerged into that world
yeah but they were doing three lower
body workouts a week and recovering from
them I'm going bodybuilders tell you to
train legs one day a week and I'm like
they're doing a knee dominant movement
and a hinging movement every training
session and then they're doing glute
activation work and I'm like why do you
have to do glute activation work well
you have to wake up the glutes in all
three planes why can't we turn those
into strengthening movements why are we
using little bands and doing 10 glute
Bridges let's load those suckers up
that's what gave me the idea so anyway
yeah it's interesting that I came up
with my ideas of hypertrophy
because of the strength coaching world
but keep going yes okay so the summary
for training men versus women in this
case what you're honing in on is the
fact that we don't necessarily on
aggregate as a general statement not
every woman not every man right just
you're saying you've trained probably
tens of thousands of women at this point
have been through your programs and
things like that what you're just saying
is on average most people that have come
through your systems want more glute
development want to have bigger glute
muscles where men Al maybe want big
glutes but also want bigger arms and
things like that the other thing that
you would want to think about here is
there's often a case when women don't
want hypertrophy in certain areas so
they often times will want bigger glutes
but not want bigger thighs right so part
of what you're talking about here and
all the the exercises and the
methodologies you just laid out are ways
that can help you potentially grow the
glutes without also then growing the the
the thighs and other parts did I have
that
and and by the way that was a blog post
I wrote in 2010 and I realized this is a
thing and say you don't have big glutes
and you're a woman and then from the
side view I go and get your quads and
hamstrings bigger yeah and then your
glutes don't grow they look even smaller
now it's proportion right and that's
something that men can't seem to Fathom
because why would you not want big quads
and hammies but if you have a certain
aesthetic you know a lot of
Asian women that I've trained who have
muscular quads but then flat glutes they
don't want to do more squats and I'm
trying to get them to I'm going squats
are good for your glutes and and they go
no they grow my quads
Brett I'm I'm you have me front
squatting 155 and my quads are huge I
don't want to do squats anymore yeah
I've had to learn I've learned this over
many many decades of training women so
you actually make their glutes
proportionally look smaller when you do
that so it depends on the if you train
the thin person that needs muscle
everywhere versus the person who has big
legs and flat so and we all have the
right to train I mean every man does it
so every ma every bro has problem areas
and strong points and so you look at all
everyone who you know there people's
training splits and we all have a
preference that we throw in that makes
our training unique compared to everyone
else's right so you're not necessarily
saying there's a difference in
physiology
it's just goals it's the goals the
physiology I think doesn't you don't
even really need to take that yes you
you you know all of it all the
differences in hormones and everything
and the recovery differences and stuff
but I don't think that the that has to
change much at all it's just a matter of
preference and then some women who are
listening to this will be like why would
you not want to grow the quads and
hammies or I don't care about glutes I
get I just want to be strong and that's
fine but we're talking about the masses
yeah and most women they look at the
human body and they go I want to split
it up this way I want they look at the
lower body and say I want to do that
three times a week and upper body they
typically do some do none yeah some do
twice a week two two upper body sessions
some just do full body training and work
it into their I would say with my
programs that right for like booty by BR
it's three full body days and but here's
the deal you do one press one compound
press could be vertical could be
horizontal you do one pole compound
whether it's a chin up a pull down or a
row and you do that three times a week a
lot that beats what most of them are
doing for body part split training yeah
and and and I don't want to go off on a
big tangent here but with like booty by
BR I I will tell them I want you getting
10 chinups eventually and they're like
what I can't even do one well keep doing
negatives but having that goal will do
more for your upper body development
then having your one back day a week
where you do these wimpy pull downs and
put it on 70 lbs CU that's what all my
girls will want to just put on 60 and 70
they don't go to 80 90 I'm like you're
you what do you weigh I weigh 1 130 then
you need to be doing 130 you want to be
able to do chin offs you better be doing
130 for reps yeah and anyway but that
that tends to develop their upper bodies
really really well and then you know a
lot of women especially in bikini they
want the the the side Del so throw in
your ladder raises
but um it depends on the wom but they
tend to want to do upper body twice a
week and some of them will have a back
day in a shoulder day and I don't think
that's as wise as having two upper body
days because of frequency but anyway
they they always have at least two lower
body workouts a week y always two
sometimes three and some girls go crazy
and want like to train glutes every day
I got creative in how to make that work
because they're obsessed yeah and I get
it we've all been there but they're like
I want to train glutes every day how
could you do that well it's doable it's
just you got to do more shortened uh
short muscle position stuff more band
work and then people will say B suck
okay how come during covid people's
upper glutes grew like crazy because
they got a glute loop around doing tons
of abduction because they're bored as
hell so they they work today's episode
is sponsored by momentus momentus makes
the highest quality supplements on the
market period many of you know me and
you know that I do not trust the vast
majority of supplement companies and for
good reason many Studies have shown that
anywhere between 10 to up to 40% of
supplements have accidental contaminants
intentional alterations mislabeling or
other serious issues but momentus is
different I literally spent years
vetting the company their products and
leadership team before personally
officially partnering with them in 2023
every single one of moment's products is
third-party tested to ensure quality and
many are even NSF certified for sport
now while I love all of their products
the ones I use the most both personally
and with my clients are what I call the
big three and these are the omega-3 fish
oil creatine and newly improved whey
protein formula these three supplements
have fantastic data supporting their
benefits whey protein forward lean
muscle mass Omega-3s for brain health
and creatin for both muscle and brain
support and they have been shown to be
very safe across basically all
populations of people Young old men
women Etc now nobody has to use
supplements and I hope you never feel
pressured to do so but if you're
interested in supplements it's important
that you get them from the highest
quality providers you don't want mercury
in your fish oil or lead in your way of
protein or anything like that so that's
why I stick exclusively to momentus if
you'd like to give momentus a try go to
Liv mous.com perform to get 20% off your
order again that's
live.com perform to get 20%
off I'm uh I'm very familiar with the
Booty by Brett program my wife does it
she loves it uh it's three days a week
of total body every day and then you
have I apologize if you have to listen
to my voice if you hear it in the
background I
don't you're if anything it helps me uh
it's three days a week total body and
then there's two additional bonus days
that are just for the glutes that you do
so that's what you're referring to when
you your program is such that if you
only want to do three days a week fine
if you also want to do four or five you
can sort of add those things on and the
way that you've gotten around that as
you just mentioned is those additional
days you just call it a pump but it's
non-damaging non- fatiguing things that
will stimulate a little bit of growth
but it's not going to crush you yes for
your next workout because those three
workouts are when you're getting your
true maximum mechanical tension and
stimuli and things like that so I I want
to walk through that whole program but
before we go side note on mechanical
tension I just called Brad up I'm like
Brad why do we say mechanical tension
what what what else could it be
psychological
tension let's drop the word mechanical
it's just tension muscular tension on
the muscle what why do we have to say
mechanical anyway keep going um okay all
the way back though you started off your
career uh you mentioned a little bit of
your backstory I've heard you know
before you you didn't have large glutes
as a kid you wanted to develop them so
you kind of got focused in this area I I
said initially where I had first saw
your stuff was again I don't even know H
probably before 2010 I don't know when
did you start writing uh for for things9
for tenation stuff all the time over
there they like it's very funny the
strength conditioning nerds are going to
understand this the rest of you probably
won't but these things like T Nation
were like the only thing we had T nation
was the greatest and like early 2000s
some of the Articles were wild on there
and then there' be people like you and
I'm like my God this is a like this is a
dissertation this is references top
strength coaches you wanted to be a top
how earn your yeah actually like a
little bit of a side note you're the
example I also give of people think that
wow you got a million followers because
you did no no no like you were famous in
this whole field way before Instagram
existed from things like putting your
chops in on those articles speaking at
scientific conferences before you had a
PhD I don't even know if before you had
a master's degree um but you were using
science as best you could in application
so you spent I don't know what was it at
least 10 years um just purely coaching
and writing for the most part you have
probably 25 years of lifting yourself 33
years of
lifting 28 years of coaching 28 years of
coaching and and this is a lot of high
volume personal coaching you have to be
in the top half a percentile of people
with a PhD in the field in terms of
coaching hours yeah like not that many
people there right so at what point
uh in that Journey did you get super
focused on the glutes you mentioned why
the the personal side and then I'm going
to ask this
inflammatory on purpose when did you
Barett contas invent the hip thrust okay
so and I'm a little bit smiling when I
say that I I know some of the backstory
but I actually don't know the whole
answer here so yeah I think you'll be
pleased to hear it okay so when I was 16
years old so I'm 48 um so when I was 16
it was
1992 I'm I I wanted to lift weights for
two reasons and maybe every guy does
this in the beginning to stand up to
bullies and to get laid I look I would
look at my body in the mirror my friends
were like athletes and they were
developing and I'm like I'm this scrawny
who what girl would ever want to see me
naked I I wish I had the confidence that
other people do that don't care that
just have the Gift of Gab and women love
them but I was like I was insecure I was
like why would anyone want to ever hook
up with me I don't I I'm so scrawny and
I hated being bullied more than anyone I
remember getting my like back when when
when we grew up it was kind of worse now
I was a teacher for six years I taught
high school math for six years it's not
as bad there have anti-bullying policies
thank God but back then I'd have some
kid come up and slam my head into the
locker or something and I one I one time
I was out at an event and there some
guys like I want to hear you talk if I
hear you talk I'm going to hit you in
the face and he was the toughest guy in
the school I didn't speak the whole
night and all of a sudden he I someone's
like Brett Brett and I'm like I can't
talk and then I I answered them and he
happened to be coming up and he just hit
me in the
jaw um and I'm I was like oh I wish I
was bigger than him I wish I could bully
him and that's what I really fueled me
to start lifting weights but I heard two
two specific instances I heard uh these
girls saying I I can't wait to go to
football practice and watch the guys
training I love staring at their butts
and I'm like oh great I'm going to be a
40-Year-Old Virgin you know women want
glutes I I don't even I look so bad from
behind my butt and then and then the
next story is I'm playing golf with my
sister's boyfriend bending over the
swing we're on the ninth hole and he's
like and it's so funny cuz he became so
descriptive he was like you know Brett
your back goes right into your legs it's
like you're missing the glue IAL
musculature most people have like a
prominence that juts out and you're just
your back goes right in your legs and
I'm like why do you feel so comfortable
talking about my biggest insecurity I
remember just going I am not okay with
this I'm going to do something about
this so I started reading everything I
could and in the bodybuilding mags you
had just read their leg day they didn't
talk about glutes it was what does
Ronnie coland do do for his quads and
hammies CU they will not mention glutes
it's like he who is the muscle whose
name shall not be mentioned it's bizarre
they still to this day have this
homophobic association with glutes and
with hip thrust it's weird I I I cover a
lot of it on my Instagram like my my
Idols you know Tom Tom plats the first
thing he ever posted on his Facebook
page was dro the useless hip Thruster
I'm like he didn't want to make a post
about and he's my Tom plads his legs
like Lee Priest just made a I just
responded an interview and he's like
bashing hipat thrust so bad and if if if
you're a if you're a man doing hip
thrust take your tampon out and it it's
it's funny so I had to learn about
glutes through um other you know
basically through bodybuilders but what
they did for the leg days but also
through other resources and when I was
19 years old my cousin bought me this
book the complete guide to to butt and
leg development and and that was 1995 I
still have the book it's on my coffee
table in Vegas I still flip through it
still in mint condition but I I read it
you on Christmas I just left the party
and went in my room and read it for like
2 hours came back to the party I'm like
this is my favorite present how did you
know and he goes dude I've never met
someone so obsessed with the glutes and
you know it was 1995 and since then my
enthusias my enthusiasm for glutes has
never diminished I'm still just as
excited but it was because I had no
glutes and no one becomes the glute guy
if they just born with good glute
genetics cuz if you have good glute
genetics guess what you never need to do
an isolation movement you just Squat and
then you're the guy going LOL just squat
quit doing that stupid Kickback quit
doing that stupid exercise just squat
you know yeah I'm I'm gonna be real
honest like that was definitely me for a
good decade or more that's a part of my
physique that it you know grows very
easy and very well and so I definitely
dismissed much of these things in fact
more than that I was pretty aggressive
earlier in my career like you don't need
any these things just squat just squat
uh it took me age
like it does everybody else to go oh you
know what not everyone's like me right
so I don't need to emphasize and as you
age you get injuries injuries are what
taught me a lot half of what I know is
by working around stuff you get an
injury and you work around stuff you're
like oh my God I like this or oh my God
I came back stronger yeah I I was
missing something so you asked about the
hip thrust so it's October 10th 2006
there's a date exact date I'm watching
UFC uh UFC fights with my girlf at the
time her name was jeie and you know UFC
fights in Phoenix Arizona or Scottsdale
come on at like 9 10 o'clock so we're
watching the
fights and I'm I didn't care who won it
was Ken Shamrock versus Tito Ortiz their
third fight I don't care who wins I just
want it to be a good fight because I
like I was in Phoenix on that fight by
the way really that's crazy were within
a few miles of each other yeah I was at
Athletes Performance really yeah yeah
they okay so I know exactly where that
that that was back before it was ex ex
exos or whatever yeah and so uh I'm
watching the fights and I'm like man
Tito you know mounts him and I'm like
Ken do something don't just lay there CU
I had a twin brother growing up and we
would always you know grapple and you'd
straddle the person you'd be K bucking
like a Bronco eventually you'd Buck the
person off I had done a couple years of
Jiu-Jitsu training I know PE the
Jiu-Jitsu guys can say oh if you have
your hooks in but the in MMA they don't
have their hooks in you can if you're
really freak isy strong a hip a a good
hip bump or whatever they call it now
but a a powerful glute Bridge can help
get you out of that and glutes help in a
lot of ways in in MMA but anyway I I
started thinking at the time I'm
like that should be an exercise now at
that time I'm reading articles on
tenation from Eric Cressy and these guys
saying do these glute Bridges and I
would do them and I'm like I love these
I love the way it feels but I could do a
100 so I was go how could you load that
also you're limited by the ground how
could you sink deeper I went out to my
garage I had an idea and I thought I'm
going to move my glute ham developer a
few feet away from my reverse hyper I
called jeie jeie come out here help me
she gets out there she's like why can't
we do this tomorrow and I'm like fine
I'll do it myself yeah I'll do it myself
and I'm trying to move this ghd across
the floor but I did it and then I'm like
a a male weighs an average male weighs
about 180 lb that's 4 45 lb plates I
didn't think of the idea to use the
barbell for a long time I took four
plates I put a dip belt and it was so
hard cuz I stood in the dip belt tried
to get up to my legs and then I had to
lay back on the glute ham developer
shimmy the weight belt up to my lap and
put my feet on the reverse hyper oh this
is super safe oh they could split apart
and you fall I know I sunk all the way
down thrust it up one I remember I got
to like
15 and I felt my left glute started I
felt like it was going to I was going to
pull it I was like God it's I'm I'm
worried I'm going to tear this thing if
I keep going so I set the weight down
and I'm like oh my God I have a pump
from one set I had never felt that
feeling before in 2006 and I went I went
out to my front yard looked up in the
sky I'm not religious I'm not even very
spiritual and I looked up in the sky I
go I'm going to spend the rest of my
life making this exercise is as popular
as humanly possible from this point on
my whole life changes and I knew it and
it was just this random where your life
is going this way and now it's going
this way and so people will say so this
is crazy so I start giving it to all my
clients I'm giving it with body weight
I'm and then I'm like figure out
different ways to load it and then my
aunt says you should you I said I want
to write an article for teen asan I
think I'm ready now this is going to be
my first which it was dispelling the
glute myth that was my first article
that was your first one that was the
article heard around the world because I
come out of the gates strong and I said
I didn't know that was your first one
and so I'm like this is the way you
build your glutes I have me hip dressing
405 people around the world started
doing it right away that's the time when
people would have said this is awkward
Brett we're doing that that was heard
around the tation back then they had
that Forum of course I was meeting guys
down the road like when I went and got
my PhD this guy from New Zealand this
guy's Sam he's like do you remember the
day you post that article I went and did
him I did
405 and because he's a powerlifter he's
like it was awesome do you remember that
was me so the very next day guys in New
Zealand guys all over the world were
doing it if someone was doing them that
would have been the time people would
like BR this is awkward we're doing this
here no one was doing hip thrust they
never existed but now the weirdest thing
happened in the world at that time I so
it took me a while to think of using a
barbell I told my aunt about it she goes
sounds like you need to invent something
and I go I don't know how to invent
anything yeah and she goes sure you do
you were always good at drawing draw
some up right now I did I applied for a
patent I still have the patent I don't
enforce my patent I could probably make
an extra $2 million a year if I enforced
it I feel guilty because I want there to
be as many hip thrust machines as
possible and so but yeah they're all
patent on the I have the patent
since I think I was awarded in maybe
2009 and um you can pull it up you can
Google Brett contas patent comes up on
Google you can see my original patent
all my
drawings um but it took me a while to
think of the barbell hip dress so my
first invention was a
scorcher and it was like that idea a
rounded backpad I had a angled foot
plate but it was this monstrosity but
that's so I opened up lifts my first gym
in
Scottdale that's all we did for hip
thrust was always off the scorcher never
anything else and we did three types of
hip thrust we did uh band hip thrust
because I said you need bands and it
needs to be anchored low so there's
tension at the start and tension at the
top so the thing was elevated and then
there was band tension from way down low
but you get to the top and it was like
insane so we did band hip thrust we did
single leg hip thrust and I gave a to
gunar Peterson he trained JLo back then
he's like Brett this is JLo's favorite
exercise but you need handles on this I
wonder if he remembers this you need
handles on this so they don't wobble
around so I put handles on the unit it
was great single legegg hip thrusts off
the scorcher are amazing because it's
actually changes the strength curve it's
hardest at the bottom yeah and you can
do that off two benches if you get two
benches and you actually go all the way
down to where your butt touches the
ground and then comes up it is hard off
the bottom yep so we would do single leg
sinking really deep coming up and then
we'd do barbell but the barbell were
hilarious this is what we did in my
first Gym trainer on this side trainer
on this side so we'd have to have every
time you did someone did Barber H they
like coach I'm ready and we'd have to
run over we'd be training like 10 people
at a time we'd run over two trainers
pick the barbell up the person slides
underneath oh gets in position drop it
in their lap they do their s of hip
thrust then we pick the bar you get out
of it and we did that for 2 years and by
the way I remember when I said why can't
you use the barbell the thing is it
would hurt you need padding and I
googled thick bar padding I googled this
in like you know 2008 and Hampton was
the only one making this thick barbell
pad for squats and that became so I made
Hampton a lot of money until people
started making their own oh wow squat
sponge the squat sponge came out and
then like we started making ours and uh
but people also use the ERX balance pads
so we'd use those too those were the
game changer for the hip thrust so all
right so
now I decide to write a an an ebook
because when I blogging was popular back
in the day you blogged but you needed a
money maker so I made an ebook I'm like
I can't be doing telling people do these
hip thrusts off the scorcher they don't
have a scorcher how can I make this
mainstream well they could do it off a
bench when you've only done the the
scorcher and then you It Off the Bench
you're like I don't feel it on my
hammies yeah I don't feel like I'm
sinking deep enough uh it just doesn't
feel right but then you get used to it
so whatever you do the most you like and
then everything else kind of feels weird
right but anyway we start doing off the
bench because I'm like I need to teach
everyone how to do it using regular
equipment no one did a barbell hips off
a bench for a couple years now I didn't
just think of the barbell hip thrust I
also thought of the barbell glute bridge
and the single leg hip thrust and you're
sitting here going Brett you're looking
me in the face saying no one ever did a
single leg hip thrust no no one ever sat
on a bench and did a single leg hip
thrust at least there's no evidence of
it now okay so prove me wrong so when I
wrote my glute ebook I did my research
you know I'm a researcher I'm not lazy I
I searched for a whole week of my life
like eight hours a day I thought of
every term you could come up with for
the first term could be pelvic floor
supine glute hip what ever and then the
second term could be raise lift thrust
Bridge um pushup like and I and I did
every combination of those and I
searched 30 pages deep I would go to
forums and search I did see like someone
glute bridging a keg um
I I found uh later on I found some
evidence so here's if you're a Bret
contus hater I'm going to give you four
pieces of evidence you can use against
me okay the first piece is
the evolution of the bench press so I
have this book from
1924 super strength um by Alan Calver
and it's it's 101 years old and so
anyway real quick I'm gonna I'm gonna
fast forward to modern day if I made a
post right now like if you post this
clip if you were to if we were to
collaborate on a post there would be at
least 10 people that write LOL I was
doing those in the '90s yeah I was doing
those in the 2000s and they remember it
that way I'm not doubting that they
think that I'm not saying they're lying
they're just they don't have good memory
they were doing that after 2009 yeah you
know um they or they'll be like my dad
was doing that and I go I always say
okay I'm a historian I I would love to I
would love to talk to the people how did
you do it what padding did you use what
set and rep schemes how frequently how
how strong were the people
but there's no evidence and what they
will always say this is crazy to me cuz
we've reached a period of time where
people are so insanely stupid that they
think that we don't have history of
anything before camera phones yeah so
I'll say prove it like give me evidence
I'm happy to I'll send out a newsletter
hey turns out I didn't invent the hip
thrust this person did I will give
credit and they'll go LOL like we had
camera phones back then and I'm like oh
my God I have a book that's 101 years
old with 200 pictures in the back of it
in black and white 100 years ago we had
cameras we brought cameras to the gym we
have a whole history before camera
phones exist and these people are
so inex it's like inexplicable how
insanely stupid they are they are the
dumbest so anyway it's not that you
necessarily uh maybe didn't invent the
hip thrust but you have yet to find
trainer invented the hip thrust in 2003
that's the only evidence I have she was
a stability okay so I'll go for the four
pieces number one is Beyonce in 2003
she's on a v VHS is that the VH VM VH1
VH1 there you go
mtvs yeah the MTV channel like the the
counterpart VH1 had a series called
rocking bodies and someone sent me this
and I'm like this was not this was after
2006 no it was not and she's on a
ability ball and she's got a little
barbell and she's doing hip thrust
that's the only time I've ever seen a
barbell hip thrust being performed but
it is with like a 30 PB barbell yeah and
she doesn't have the best form but I'd
never seen it until I I didn't see that
until a few years ago so you could say
Beyonce's trainer it shows her in the
video there's a little exra so whoever
this is she could be given credit for
inventing the hip you find her name
right um and then if you look at the
book okay that book I told you about in
1995 it has pelvic raises it shows glute
Bridges and single glute Bridges but it
doesn't show them with weight but if you
go to the back of the program the back
the back of the book has programs and it
says in one part weighted pelvic raises
okay but it doesn't show how to weight
it gotcha now that would be off the
ground but that would be a weighted
glute Bridge or whatever but it doesn't
say how now you look at the book super
training by Mel this is a classic
classic there is a some pictures from
1977 credited to Yuri veros shansi this
Russian Sports scientist rest in peace
and these are all hip rust it looks like
Kamas Sutra drawings but they're all hip
rust and you can see these are single
legegg hip thrust there's one the person
against a bench and they're pushing
against their hips that's an isometric
hip thrust and then there's single
legegg where you got your foot on a
kabel on your foot and you're doing
single leg thrust and their special
exercise to develop sprinting who would
have known that 50 years later we'd now
have evidence that hip thrust are
actually better for sprinting than the
ver than the vertical hip extension
exercises so that was ahead of its time
but these are H these are hip thrust
variations and then another piece was
from the late 1800s early 1900s the
invention of the bench press so they
didn't always have benches so what they
first started in the strongman back then
they' they'd have to kind of do a pull
over and press you just were laying on
the ground you just had to get the bar
over your head yep then they started
making bigger discs and you could roll
it over um which is what what I ended up
doing with BC strength with hit Thruster
plates even bigger but back then they
had to get it over their head and then
they do a press and then people started
realizing if I so was like you know
Arthur Saxon had the record then like
George hackin Schmid and then this Joe
Nord Quest and he did it from a he would
Elevate his cuz you could Bend you could
if you turn it into a glute bridge and
turn into decline you were even stronger
yep and then some guys started realizing
hell I'm just gonna they call it belly
toss so they would put it on their belly
and toss it up and lock it out so then
that was the belly toss method and then
some guy named George
L he was so flexible he could just go
and Bridge all the way up to lock out
put his hips down oh nice and then at
that point they're like this isn't even
using pressing muscles this is silly so
um so the the powers that be um Hoffman
what is Hoffman's name Jo Bob Hoffman
Bob Hoffman Bob Hoffman decided this is
stupid let's get away with all this yeah
you let's just do the strict strict uh
floor press and that's when benches
start coming along so they were doing
like belly tosses
um but for one rep yeah not for reps and
it wasn't with the goal of building
glutes it was to have a stronger bench
which is what you'll see high school
kids doing now in gyms doing anything
they can to get a stronger bench press
right and interestingly back then bench
press is some of the same
criticisms are what you see of hip
thrust today quit being L they were a
lazy man's exercise right standing
exercise are functional this is how you
build the real functional muscle who
wants to artificially expand the pecs
these aren't you know functional musle
the real muscles are your shoulders and
your biceps and you should you should be
doing curls and overhead presses who
lays down to do an exercise and then
bodybuilders um you know started doing
the bench um and and then it took off
and then yeah but it was criticized in
the beginning and it's it's going to be
bad for your posture it's going to be un
nonfunctional it's going to lead to
injury and then people ignored them and
then it now is the most popular exercise
today and the same thing is happening
with hip thrust now with the um
invention of these plate loaded devices
and these selectorized devices those are
the bestselling pieces of equipment
right now yeah it's like you're a modern
gym the ladies want the hip thrust
machines I would be hard pressed to
believe nobody in the history of the
world ever did a loaded hip thrust
before bre contr but of
course well that's what I tell people
then cuz I had a coach tell me he was
doing I go how come you never posted
about it why didn't you you didn't
realize it was going to be popular yeah
yeah it's just like that's the way
history works yeah it just wasn't very
popular at all before you so at minimum
we could say you're the one that brought
it to the Lexicon sure you were not
doing it in every gym it was not
certainly in studios now you you can't
go to a gym that doesn't have a hip
thrust machine of some kind yeah so yeah
no one will argue that Bret Canter
popularized it I just don't I just don't
like being like basically being called a
fraud as if I'd take credit for
something I never did in fact back in
the day people were like calling it the
contus hip thrust or were two bloggers
calling it The CHT and I'm like don't
make it about me this I want this to be
Pera on its own everyone knows I
invented it and then now no no one knows
I invented it yeah because the world
changed social media kind of became a
copycat game back in our day we gave
credit we always gave credit credit if
you didn't give credit you were you know
dead in your tracks totally today's
episode is brought to you by Parker
University Parker is the only University
in the world dedicated exclusively to
Human Performance it's also my new
academic home I first heard of Parker
after attending their neuroon seminar
and was stunned I've been to countless
clinics and conferences and nobody is
even close to Parker Seminars the
speakers the setup and the total
experience are frankly jaw-dropping all
their seminars are great but the
upcoming Las Vegas show which is going
down March 20th through 22nd is going to
be extra special it's featuring speakers
like doctors Andrew huberman Tommy wood
Gabriel lion and more but on top of that
I'm personally hosting a co- seminar at
the same time so imagine going to a
phenomenal lecture on how the nervous
system works then popping over and
lifting some weights with me personally
grabbing lunch and then settling in for
a talk on how NASA scientist Cody
Burkhart is preparing human human bodies
for Life on Mars tickets for this
incredible event are on sale now at a
special rate of only
$599 but this price will increase as the
dates get closer so do not wait and yes
you heard that right
$599 get you full access to the entire
Parker seminar expo hall nightlife and
social events plus two full days of
learning and lifting weights with me in
the gym and my friend Dan Garner to see
the exact schedule list of speakers and
get signed up visit Parker seminars.com
one more time that's Parker seminars.com
I can't wait to see you there okay so
really fast uh before we go into some
some more details about how to train in
some of the things walk me through the
difference between a hip thrust and a
glute Bridge you mentioned single leg
glute Bridges you mentioned different
loading strategies for people that are
thinking like I don't know the
difference here um what is that
difference again between a glute Bridge
a hip thrust why does it matter if
you're on the ground it's a glute Bridge
you can do that one leg two two legs
best way to do is off the Smith machine
though because you're on a bench it's
plate loaded you just load the plates up
and you can go all the way down to the
ground you can all the way go sit on the
bench sometimes if the plates if you're
a smaller person you don't even get to
touch down before the plates touch down
yep so your back is on the ground your
feet are on the ground and you're
elevating your your hips up in the air
with some load on your hips that's a
glute Bridge that's a glute Bridge one
leg two leg and if you elevate your feet
from that position it's a foot elevated
glute Bridge so you put your feet up on
a bench yep yep which allows you to get
your hips up higher and yep increase the
range of motion but doesn't increase the
quad activity right um if if you now you
elevate your shoulders that's a hip
thrust uh so now you're putting your
back up on a bench put your back up on a
bench and now if you elevate both your
shoulders and feet that's a dual
elevated or foot elevated hip thrust yep
so yeah basically hip thrusts are going
to build your quads a little bit more
probably if you want all glute growth
and no quad no hamstring no
adductor that then the glute bridge is
probably your lift because the thing is
you could say do Kickbacks do these
exercises but these are not exer is easy
to progressively overload over the years
glute Bridges you can and hip thrust
that's why they're so effective they're
very conducive to Progressive overload
same with squats Deus and bench press
the most the most effective exercises
you can keep loading them you can a
standardized range of motion a way to
perform it you do it this way every time
when you get stronger you're utilizing
Progressive overload you should be
growing muscle over time yes there are
neural effects and coordination effects
but you should grow muscle over time and
that's why I say make it a goal to hip
thrust 315 for 20 that's your best bet
to getting glutes and people 315 pounds
for 20 Reps for a 250 pound man so it
doesn't matter um yeah it's kind of
crazy because you think every other lift
you're like well Size Matters what what
do they weigh but I found that when
you're bigger like hip thrust it's
easier to hip thrust when you're smaller
um it's just more comfortable you don't
when you're bigger your belly gets in
the way you're just cramped in there and
body weight adds to it so I I I I would
like to say you know maybe 2.5 times
body weight for 20 reps but really 315
for 20 is very simple probably the best
metric if there had to be one but
obviously with genetics yeah yeah
gentics on that really really fast what
again what you're saying is you
personally having trained again
thousands if not tens of thousands of
individuals not NFL players 90% female
probably most of them sub 200 lb um what
one or two of them have ever been able
to hip thrust 315 for 20 like how many
no every client I have can every client
you have and and not just all right you
go to an liment weightlifting gym what
are you going to see snatches and
cleaning jerks well what equipment oh
yeah you're going to see barbells well
you're going to see plates squat stands
yeah platforms power racks that's it
yeah what what are you gonna see if you
go to glute lab hip thrust stations in
San Diego we've got like 12 against the
wall just against the one wall on the
astr turf that's what we do here and the
other thing is yeah if you trained at
Westside back in the day do you think
you would have been stronger yeah well
if you train at glute lab you think
you're 315 for five is impressive and
then you look at these girls and they're
freaks yeah freaks they're doing 4495
they're doing 585 didn't you have a girl
just do 800 or something like that so
there's a there
I have not I've seen one legit 800lb hip
thrust from a woman her name was Daria
now the problem is people don't lock it
out a full legit lock out I've been
watching hip thrust millions and
millions of reps I'm very skilled at
seeing did you reach full hip extension
they have these um Guinness Book of
World Records and like contest now you
see and I get tagged in them like they
didn't even come close to locking it out
yeah you got to reach full hip extension
this girl Daria she did 810 or 800 I
think it was 800 legit in training she
had did one of my strong lifting
competitions the thing is hip Thruster
last so you've already done squads and
Deads she she didn't get seven I think
it was like 7:35 or something she well
nonetheless call me still impressed at a
700 lb uh my CL Carly she hit 765 legit
full lockout one of the coolest
experiences of my life and I think she
could have done 800 there's another girl
Katie sonero I think could get to an 800
lb hip thrust legit she's doing the
rotisserie one
now that's using the rotating pad that's
oh that slides with yeah yeah yeah
that's on my Thruster 3.0 the girls like
it
more that also changes the torque angle
curved to where it's hardest off the
ground the lockout becomes easy oh CU
you can roll back yeah it just changes
it to where I did it the other cuz I did
it for the first time it was always hard
at the bottom it feels I'm too I got a
belly you know it's too I'm too wedged
in so I did like I did it with bands and
I did I'm I think I did four 405 for 12
and my client Dre is like lol coach I'm
stronger than you I'm like Dre it's my
first time I did them I'm still stronger
than you I hope I'm stronger I'm yeah
literally twice your size um so I did it
again and it was it's it's it's really
hard at the bottom and then it gets
easier as you come up it's really
different in fact at the top I'm like I
feel like I'm GNA tip over it's kind of
you're kind of scared that you're gonna
flip over but that's an interesting
debate because now you're changing so
with that rotating pad you a lot of The
Men Who criticize the HP say well it's
easy at the bottom hardest at the top
well you can make it with this design
you can change that around yep but
anyway now there's that Katie's doing
like 900 lbs for four reps or something
it's crazy or yeah maybe it's 800 for
four but she's she's crazy anyway
there's women can get
stronger than men at this I would love
to relatively relatively stronger I have
never seen a man legit lock out a
thousand well maybe this guy I posted it
there's one guy who looked like he had a
legit lock out but you see the strongest
powerlifters in the world they never
lock it out and they're doing like you
know they can get to 7 800 lbs but it's
really interesting and I think it has to
do with that women have possibly better
leverage at lockout especially with
their adductors some of their muscles
but maybe their glutes can get their
glutes can probably get relatively maybe
a little bit bigger or at least they're
training glutes three times a week it's
going to get bigger but I think they're
maybe because they're not training their
hamstrings and everything too so their
lockout strength tends to be amazing and
I always think it's funny what 10 years
ago I'd have all these girls that are
like I saw this bodybuilder in the gym
and of course that bodybuilder has a
crush on one of my girls so they're
flirting and then they see him do and
hip thrust or glute bridge and they're
like oh let me see if I can do that they
can't do it and that's because they have
strong glutes down deep in a hips flexed
position totally they can do half Reps
for days but then you have them come up
all the way and lock it out they lack
that lockout strength which is something
you will hear um what's his face
Nautilus inventor um Arthur Arthur Jones
talk about how when people would start
to use the machines they're so strong in
the stretch position y they're so weak
here it takes them a while to you know
they're so weak here there's this
massive imbalance throughout the range
of motion so yeah so I I I do think that
um there are some anatomical differences
that make women stronger at hip thrust
but also just comes down to for women
the hip thrust is their bench press you
know guys ask you how much do you bench
women how much do you thrust you know
right yeah so you mentioned now a
handful of anatomical terms and you've
you've peppered in a little bit about
how to train them differently but I want
to complete that picture if we can so um
just give me the really basic overview
of the glute Anatomy right uh couple of
different muscles there and then what I
really want to get to on that is how do
I train them differently if I need to so
if I want my glutes to get bigger do I
need to be having bands do I should I
not use them like give me that whole
picture of saying okay Brett I want my
butt bigger do all I have to do is hip
thrust do I need to add anything else
what are adductors complete that whole
picture about what am I looking at
Anatomy wise and then what implications
do I have for training okay so
anatomically you have attachments at the
ilum the sacrum and the coxics mostly
the sacrum like so you the glutax will
tailbone yeah attaches a little bit to
the the pelvis you know and then the
sacrum and a little bit to the coxics
and then it inserts onto the glal
tuberosity of the femur but also onto
the IT band and it's your glutes
attached to the back of your thigh like
the back of your thigh muscle kind of
the lateral edge of it though right
there aren't many muscles like the
glutes it's like a it's like a
quadrilateral is that why don't I
remember this I used to teach geometry
it's a it's a it's it's almost
rectangular shaped in a way right well
if we contrast this s to the like the
quadriceps muscle groups those all come
into the patella have one insertion
point on that fr of your knee that's
that knob down there so what you're
talking about is the glutes are
different because they don't have that
single point of Landing broadly B fan of
because they attach okay so because they
attach to the femur and pelvis and
sacrum that alone is a big deal but now
you look at their fascial attachments so
first of all there's some fascial
attachments to the pelvic floor giving
it some implications with that um kind
of like urinary and cons in like the
pelvic floor function right um then you
have the attachment onto the IT band
which then attaches down to the tibia so
now it it's almost like that's that can
be considered a tendon yep so it makes
it uh that would make it a biarticular
muscle you know yeah meaning it's going
to both extend your hip and rotate it
out right because it is attached the
attaches to the
tibia not just all right like okay so
you're talking about when it contracts
I'll get to that in a second okay but
also attaches to the Theo lumbar fascia
to the glut medius fascia a lot of stuff
kind of Blends in together so if you
consider the thorco lumo fascia into the
lat and the lat on on to the arm you've
got kind of the glute Max possibly
affecting things up and down the chain
from the arm to the lower leg so your
back shoulder right yeah so so for that
reason these people tend to OV
exaggerate and act like you know these
like Anatomy trains and stuff and the
fases everything and these myofascial
meridians and everything but I do think
it's if you looked at if you took a step
back and looked at the human muscular
anatomy chart or like picture you'd be
like the glutes are the Keystone they
are the Keystone muscle that's why I'm
okay being the glute guy I would not
want to be the pet guy the GL are the
Keystone they're the plant guy yeah so
they they affect a lot of things and
it's like that centerpiece so um so then
you look at the subdivisions okay so the
glute medius that's been separated into
anti and posterior divisions
subdivisions it could have it probably
has anti middle and posterior glut medus
isn't talked about that much um it but
it's it's people act like you can Target
them one one or the other and like
they're they over the glut medus
overlaps the glut Minimus how do you
target they'll be like kick out at this
angle for glut me and this angle for for
glute glute men right so you've got
glute Max is the big one we think of GLX
is so the glute me and men are up up or
outer up and outside right below your
hipbone there yeah and then the glute
Max is a diagonal shaped and the fiber
directions are you
know Pro around 40° isum they all they
they change between I can't remember
there's a couple papers looking at the
exact fiber directions but it's like and
then when it contracts you can see
bodybuilders squeezing their glutes
posing they become pretty horizontal
when you so people will say I've heard
people say oh glutax is just a hip
extensor it's just m if it was just a
hip extensor why would they be vertical
more vertical yeah um and uh they they
do three things they abduct but it's
only the upper fibers the abduct yep
meaning it takes your leg away from your
midline yeah frontal plane abduction so
frontal plane abduction if you're
standing up think jumping jacks you're
abducting the legs so the upper glutax
fibers is abduct um but the glut me and
men are the main abductors tfl as well
but glut me is like an amazing abductor
super strong at abduction frontal plane
um the lower glute Max there's evidence
that it's an adductor but I have not
found any EMG activity with
adduction now here's what's interesting
okay there's the upper and lower
subdivisions of the glute Max they seem
to have be um you know activated
uniquely through EMG and the whole GL GL
Max externally rotates the whole glute
Max extends the hip but only the upper
abduct some people say the upper is more
effective in external rotation I think
it's the entire glut Max is very
effective in ex hip external rotation
and when we swing a bat you think
because I used to just think of these
things as distinct actions think about
swinging about you're loaded up kind of
in the stretch position a little bit and
then you contract the glutes it does
three things you are going to extend the
hips you were going to abduct the hips
and you are going to rotate laterally
the hips they do all three things at
once during swinging striking throwing
um so it's that's what they're called
tripler now when you bend over and
you're in deep hip flexion now the
gluten me and men are not um they they
their moment arms change where they're
not even effective very effective at
abducting the thigh anymore maybe the
posterior are but not the middle and
anterior but now the Max becomes a
better abductor of the thigh yeah so if
you think about this like if you were to
be standing up vertical and I just said
you know do it the jumping jack action
right this is where you're lifting your
leg out to the side um if you were to do
this as a common exercise where you like
lay on your side and you lift your leg
up in the air right now in that position
what you're saying is those small upper
glute muscles glute glute medius glut
Minimus things like that might be adding
to that action but if you were to Bend
forward and now so like I'm standing
here and I'm hinging forward I'm doing a
like an a seated hip abduction seated
hip thing leaning forward now if I do it
those muscles aren't really active
anymore now that entire action has to
come from my glute Max right well I
think or likely when you you said May
the from the side line the glute meat is
the main hip abductor no argument about
it from bover position I think the
posterior subdivision would be activated
well um you're going to get some
activation of the hip extra rotators now
become horizontal plane abductors and
also the glute Max Y how efficient are
those at building them we don't know but
I do include those in the program y so
now you said how do I build glutes well
because the glutes
have first of all the glute Max has
upper and lower
subdivisions and some people would been
say there's the you know the iliac
fibers the sacral fibers and the coxial
fibers yep
they might even separate the glute Max
between three
subdivisions but definitely upper and
lower and then the glute me has multiple
subdiv in the glut man to Maxim
development them you're going to do
combine a lot of different actions
there's two studies one looking at the
glute glute size of Olympic
weightlifters and it shows that their
glute Max is larger than control sub
than sedentary subjects but their glute
me and mint are not
meaning squats do not grow your glut
medum in also the plin study showed that
squats and hip thrust neither one of
them grew your glut meus and Minimus if
you want to grow your glut me and Min
you should treat it like any other
muscle and train it dynamically through
a full range of motion and there's uh
one guy this Chasm pointed out that
we're all doing ab Junction straight out
to the side yep you really should look
at the pelvic shape and kind of go in
the plane of the glute medius
which is diagonal at 30° if you look at
how the pelvis is shaped and how the
gluten medus you should kick out the
problem is it's really hard for people
to get that right yeah you have a nice
way of showing it in a in like an educ
instructional video you look overhead
and you tell them turn this foot in and
then drive back but it's really hard
people they end up bending over Y and
then they're involving in the glute Max
more so it's it's really hard and then
do their foot go in front or in back and
then they end up at so I have ways of
teaching it but basically sometimes when
it gets when people keep screwing up
just go straight out to the side yeah
and and and so but but because the glute
me and men have multiple subdivisions
you probably should do different angles
of abduction yeah um you should go
straight out to the side you should go
at a 30 degree angle back you should
also do maybe seated hip abduction
straight up uh might develop the poster
heads more but also on the seated hip
abduction machine Bridge up doing Bridge
and do them leaning forward cuz leaning
forward for the glute Max bridged up you
could put blocks like yoga blocks
underneath you or just maintain the
bridge position for the glute me okay
what about glute Max you're going to get
the most bang for your buck with hip
extension um hip extension exercises
take them through the most range of
motion but now you start talking about
how to put the mo together the most
comprehensive program I know in 10 years
especially if I team up with you and we
start doing studies using this MRI stuff
but God that we have a lot of questions
that remain so right now my optimal
program you know the scientific studies
we have to guide us are few yeah we've
got you know Kubo from 2019 showing
deeper squats are better than shallow
squats but that for glute Max GL Max
growth but that just looked at knee
angle they were probably hinging over
and yeah they were Pro no the beginners
doing the sh are probably staying
vertical and we don't have a study
looking at super deep squats versus
parallel I think parallel would either
be more effective or same I don't think
you need to go past parallel for glute
growth there's two studies on quads
showing you deeper is not necessary uh
that Kubo study showed the same quad
growth but it showed greater adductor
and glute growth going deep and then we
so that's this the study that people
cling to about um glutes being worked
more in the stretch there's also an
unpublished study that should I I don't
know why it's not published yet by M uh
so Kickbacks grow more glute in the
stretch position but it's a straight leg
Kickback kind of weird um who does
straight leg Kickbacks uh you're not
stretching it the most you're not and
they and they only went to neutral they
didn't go into hip hyper extension so
that doesn't have a lot of ecological
validity with like how we do things in
the field so the best anyone who's
scientific right now who trains people
in real life and works with people and
then also tries to incorporate the
science all right this is what a
reasonably because you get these crazy
in every aspect of social like every
field every there's these politics you
look at anything even in your world more
of the physiology and performance World
you'll get these coaches saying this way
and this way you'll get people saying
just train glutes in the stretch
position every muscle grows best from
the stretch position but that's a
fascinating area I have every study on
it categorized into the folders We The
Verdict is not out on every exercise and
depends how if you're a beginner or
trained and how long is long enough but
what that what that whole category of
research has not looked at is com
combining them into a pro like basically
what you can recover from because it
might be that if you just could do one
set a week what would be the best thing
to do maybe it'd be a set of walking
lunges to failure all right if you can
do two sets now what if you have all the
time in the world and you don't mind
doing whatever it takes well then I
would say train three days a week at
least but what if what if what if you
could do hip thrust every day You'
probably get some people developing
overuse injuries but my point is you
could recover from that would that be
more effective than training long muscle
length twice a week yes it wouldn't be
as efficient but possibly wouldn't be as
efficient but you could recover from way
more what if you don't create any muscle
damage after a while and you just
stimulate hyper dvy and you can expedite
the rate at which muscle new muscle is
laid down we don't know there's a lot of
these questions we don't know yet so
right now train the glutes three days a
week and follow the rule of thirds the
rule of thirds is something I came up
with to illustrate this concept when
you're doing vertical exercise those are
the most demanding on the central
nervous system well it's funny because
if youve seen the research on that we
really don't have a lot of evidence that
it's more demanding on the central
nervous system yeah I'll hold my tongue
but go ahead don't we need to we need re
evidence of that because people know
what it means by vertical exercise
you're meaning squats things like that
squats deadlifts lunges step UPS bulgar
squats skater squats pistol squats good
mornings and all their variations yep
those are the vertical exercise the
horizontal are hip thrust glute Bridges
you know your single leg hip thrust um
your back extensions 45 degree hypers
your
Kickbacks but within those there's this
is what makes it so complicated you can
can make ex you can make things more
knee dominant or more hip dominant even
Kickbacks what if you did kneeling
Kickbacks yeah then you almost it's
becomes like a step up so I'm talking
about an upright Kickback you know so um
and then a a back extension off a ghd is
horizontal that's pure horizontal 45 is
halfway between but we call it
horizontal because it works the squeeze
position more than the stretch those
exercises do not beat you up in fact
after you've done them for a while they
don't beat you up much at all they don't
create nearly as much muscle damage so
those can be done more frequent
frequently and with more volume and then
lateral exercises um those are like
penalty-free volume because you never do
too much those are going to work your
more of your glut medius and stuff if
you lean forward yes you're going to
work more glut Max but they don't beat
you up we just do you
know two to six sets at the end of a
depending on someone's goals typically
at the end of the workout but if someone
really wants to grow their upper GL I
might say do start with Abdu I mean
think about it if you're really wanting
to grow your ab glutes begin with a
frontal plane abduction movement and
maybe end with one yep so then you do
the rule of thirds you do around so and
then here's another simple simple system
three times a week pick one exercise
from four categories the first category
is your thrust bridge and this could be
in any order the second is your squat
lunge and when I say squat lunge it
means split squat Step Up single leg leg
press um and then you pick a hinge and
the hinge this is where it's kind of it
could be vertical like an RDL it could
be like a 45 hyper it could be a reverse
hyper but it's more straight leggedy hip
extension and then pick a an abduction
movement the abduction could be frontal
plane it could be horizontal plane
leaning forward uh it could be hip
external rotation still so I call it
abduction like lateral rotary so you do
your vertical your horizontal your
lateral rotary but pick abduction but
also include abduction there aren't that
many hip external rotation exercises we
do two of them the cable cuff where you
spin y those are hard to master they're
hard to teach but anyway when you do
that system you will fully develop your
glut Max and glut me and Min the you
because when you do pick one from each
of those four that's how do it three
times a week don't do the same exercise
every time that's boring lots of
variation to make sure if there is an
effect of range of motion if there is an
effect on activation that you're
covering all your bases more fun and
that's when when when I see people be
like just do rdls do you imagine Rd
these girls train three times a week
first of all you can't recover from
doing squats and rdl's three times a
week with intensity with with sufficient
effort but also um yeah it's boring and
it's you you better be throwing in
single leg rdls that are not as taxi on
the low back yeah so what I found is you
cannot do too much these guys that are
telling
people here's a here's a science-based
glute workout they don't train women
because I'm telling you most of them
train three days a week they train lower
body 3 days a week these programs would
crush people would absolutely Crush
these women I get carried away sometimes
so I don't do drop sets anymore I don't
do these crazy burnouts I don't do crazy
super sets I'm not trying I don't even I
even do lower reps now than I used to
cuz we used to get carried away I even
used to do like Sumo deadlifts with the
deadlift bar and touch and go that's
like these girls can I had girls doing
315 yeah back in San Diego Ashley got 19
reps Dominique got 11 reps like CU touch
and go you can bounce that bar up you
can move and everyone's cheering you on
cool you did something good and then
you're sore for like a week a month you
can't duplicate that for a month yeah
yeah cuz you're so beat down and that's
what I mean so maybe it's muscle damage
maybe it's like damage to to fascia to
discs yep something Chris Beardsley
pointed out to me when you do a
conventional deadlift you're doing a
concentric lift right yep but what
happens to the Erectors you line you
line up in the arch yep you go to
pull the hips shoot up a little the back
rounds a little bit you pull it up the
before the bar left the ground the
Erectors went into an e you're
activating it it went into an Ecentric
so that can create more damage more
something about the spine when you
really do squats to failure deadlifts to
failure those beat up so you need a good
mix within those categories within the
the squat lunge categor some should be
bilateral some some should be unilateral
some should be more quad dominant some
should be more hip dominant meaning you
can do a high bar squat with the feet
elevated but that's going to be more
quad you can also do a low bar vertical
Shin box squat sitting back that's more
hip dominant and then that so you want
to have variety within those with the
deadlifts you want to do sometimes you
might do a conventional Sumo deadlift
sometimes an RDR or stiff leg dead but
sometimes single leg variations single
leg and even good mornings you can do
good single leg good mornings off the
Smith machine you can get good at good
mornings too people say they're
dangerous but that's because they don't
start off light and work their way up
good mornings are good variations to do
but the hinge variations should mix
between deadlift and good mornings and
then also 45s and reverse hypers and
back extensions and then the abduction
should be Blended between uh frontal and
transverse plane and there's so many
abduction movements there's sideline hip
raises extra range sideline hip my
favorite are glut medius hip thrust and
glut medus Kickbacks um you can Google
those but um but my but basically then
the hip thrust variations should blend
between you could do double leg you
could do do single egg and B stance but
mostly double egg but varum
between barbell Smith machine and plate
loaded devices but
also you're getting plenty of work in
this system you're getting plenty of
stretch position work so with the hip
thrust it doesn't always have to be
emphasizing full range or you can
emphasize the lockout in a few different
ways we do a lot of pauses at the top we
do a lot of bar plus band we connect the
bar to bands makes the lockout even
harder and you could do pulses where
you're just doing the top range of
motion if you only did hip thrust and
that was all you ever did then you
should probably do some bottom bottom
pauses bottom range of mod ways to make
the bottom heart but you get those when
you do the lunges the squats the AR and
this is the best system I've come up
with it's the most scientific way to
train the glutes as we know right now
any reasonable person would say that um
because if you said to H if you said to
like a bro okay if you put two inches on
your glutes in the next few months yeah
you think they train it one day a week
no one would train it one day a week
yeah you train it a few times a week but
you got to recover from it and you can't
get carried away in fact a lot of times
when I train my girls if I have them do
reverse lunges off the Smith machine or
the lever squat the plate loaded Squat
and they do two hard sets I'm like done
sometimes one hard set I'm like just be
done you set a PR I'm like you're going
to be sore from that and sometimes
they're like coach I'm I was so or thank
God I only did one hard set that's
something no one knows to do anymore
they don't they always just do three to
four sets yeah sometimes one and two
sets is fine as well you got to be able
to recover and if you don't recover then
what happens is this happens in my gym a
lot typically on Fridays and which sucks
is because Friday if you train Monday
Wednesday Friday you have an extra
recovery day so it'd be nice to be fresh
on Friday train hard cuz you got two
days to recover so optimally that would
be your day to push but sometimes
they're like coach I push myself hard on
Monday Wednesday I am beat down so what
they do is they do a short muscle length
day or like a they that's when they film
their their influencer workouts and they
did I'm like you didn't even do that
workout but that got the most likes so
they do variety they do their fuu wimpy
movements that PE that the men arguably
so they get pissed at that's when they
do just a uh some Kickbacks some
abductions some light bands bands and
and then they they do that on Friday
they rest Saturday and Sund and come
back Monday and they crush it yeah
because they did a wimpy workout but
that's Auto regulation that's how they
periodize but ideally you wouldn't they
wouldn't have done too much on Monday
and Wednesday to begin with so that
Friday they could have still crushed it
but that's an art unto its own how to
nail your training so that you don't
have to Delo so much and you don't have
to do radical things but that's
something we that takes a lot of years
to
master today's episode is sponsored by
ag1 ag1 is a vitamin mineral drink with
probiotics prebiotics and adaptogens
initially I was extremely skeptical of
ag1 as I am with all supplement
companies but after months of
discussions with their lead nutrition
scientist and the general team at ag1
I've been impressed by a1's commitment
to sourcing the highest quality
ingredients and constantly updating
their formulas to have the right
ingredients in the optimal amounts ag1
also rigorously test their products to
ensure that every single batch is free
of ban substances allergens heavy metals
micro pesticides herbicides residual
solvents and mot toxins it's even earned
the prestigious NSF certified for sport
thirdparty testing approval stamp now
most people in the performance space
talk a lot about macronutrients like
protein carbohydrates and fats and these
are obviously critically important but
so are the micronutrients like vitamins
and minerals and even if you're eating a
healthy diet it's often hard to get
enough of these vitamins and minerals
along with the probiotics prebiotics and
adaptogens to keep your body performing
at its best it's for these reasons and
many others that I personally take ag1
almost every day now it's of course not
a replacement for eating whole healthy
foods but it is a great way to make sure
that you're plugging in any gaps in your
nutrition to improve your energy bolster
your immune system and just generally
help promote a healthy gut microbiome
and more if you'd like to try ag1 you
can go to drink a1.com perform to
receive five free travel packs plus a
year supply of vitamin D3 plus K2 again
that's drink a a1.com perform to receive
five free travel packs plus a year
supply of vitamin D3 plus
K2 couple quick questions on that you've
made I think a couple of points really
clear to maximize glute development
whether that's growth and specifically
growth or strength but growth is for the
most part we're talking about you
haven't said these words directly but
it's clearly come through in all the
examples and the information you
provided consistency is incredibly
important right and so all the rationale
you're going back on here is we got to
be able to do this more often so we can
continue to progressively overload and
that's really been a backdrop here so as
somebody who's probably been responsible
for more butt growth than anybody on the
planet I think that's a pretty powerful
message from you that says like just do
enough to stimulate growth here but
don't annihilate so that you can keep
training for months or years and that's
where you're going to see these big big
increases yes you also used variation to
get there that is another way to keep
yourself in the game right you can use
you call them short movement arms right
these are again things not short moment
short muscle length short muscle length
right thank you these are different
exercises that You' said don't beat you
up right and what that means is your
joints and the tissue itself won't be as
hurt or sore but you'll still get a lot
of results from them so you can continue
with your Progressive overload and you
can be consist assistant right one quick
clarification on that little system
right so you pick one exercise for the
four different uh bucket areas three
days per week and you said maximize
variation am I picking say from bucket
one one exercise from Monday one
exercise that's a different one on
Wednesday and then a third different
exercise on Friday or are you saying
like every single workout pick a totally
different exercise per category that's
such a good question so
ideally what you would do is okay so
this is the component of the system I
didn't talk about rotating Focus we've
read about periodization our whole lives
right and whenever you read about
periodization it's about changing volume
and effort or like load and intensity
some intensity what does intensity mean
load or effort so I don't even say
intensity anymore but like we
basically uh you you you you you start
off with more volume lighter loads and
do more sets and then as you as you go
up in weight and get use more and more
weight and train harder and harder and
closer to failure you do less you know
so volume and so it makes an X volume
and effort make an X but but but it was
always assumed to be like what I'm
always going what what exercises the
periodization is kind of like there
aren't good books on it if you want to
read up on periodization uh like I think
my book glute lab is one of the best
because I to I talked about all the
nuances and stuff but like they never
talked about rotating the
exercises and I tell all these
powerlifters and I don't presume to know
more than the bodybuilders about
bodybuilding and the powerlifters about
powerlifting but I do think powerlifters
could get stronger because guess what
squats and Deads compete with each other
you could say they build each other but
they compete everything competes up to
like you know generally don't see people
that hold World Records in both yeah
it's usually one or the other have the
total as well but that's cuz our head
and one of them really fall if you can't
tell me that this lifter wouldn't have
gotten better at squats if he quit
focusing on Deads for a while right and
vice versa you see the same thing
weightlifting by the way snatch and
clean a jerk yeah it's hard to be best
of both yeah you one of them runs away
and the other one and you try to win
that way right so take some time you
like I I did this just recently I went
God what when have you ever prioritized
your hamstrings for like two months so I
started every workout with a uh with
either a deadlift like a stiff leg
deadlift or a good
morning and then I do two different
isolation movements for the hamstrings
when have you ever done three hamstring
movements in one workout I started doing
that oh my God it got scary for a while
I'm doing good mornings with uh
345 lbs for 15 reps I think I could have
gotten 20 but I started rounding a lot
and I'm like Y how far can I keep going
here but it's it's I oh my god I've
never really prioritized you're always
doing squats first or Deads but never
stiff leg and you're you're never really
doing as much hamstring work so anyway
I'm going to tell how I think this
applies to bodybuilding but I'm going to
tell you what I do in Booty by Brett
Booty by Brett I was realizing okay and
I got this one time I had this Epiphany
I'm like someone asked me how many
chin-ups I could do like what's my Max
you know weighted chin up and I'm like
well I I can do 12 but I could get more
if I trained for it well why don't I
train for it
well what would I do if I trained for it
I'd probably do chinups every day and
then I started thinking about all the
different lists what if you wanted to be
strongest at your bench press what would
you do what if you wanted to get
strongest at your squats what would you
do how often would you squat I'd
probably squat twice a week but I can't
deadlift hard not to failure twice a
week so I realize every lift has its own
rules and I got and then then I created
strong lifting and those are the Bas
strong lifting is like lifting but with
six lifts squats bench Deads so the
three power lifts and then chinups
military press and death and hip thrust
those are my six favorite list we got
really good in fact I would say I'm the
world's expert at getting you strong at
all six lists because that is all my
girls did what I will tell you is it's
rare like it's hard to have a 100 pound
military press strict yeah yeah
um to have 135 is insane that's that's
that's like Elite for a female um what
what I will tell you is having if you
lift if chin up you take your body
weight and you add the toes you add to
it because you're pulling your body
weight up so if you take your six lifts
your one rep max and I'm talking strict
people will will lie squatting below
parallel you know the the the
powerlifting rules yep for the three
powerlifts and then with a chin up not
starting from here starting from a dead
hang and touching your chest to the bar
not just getting your chin over chest to
Bar yep military you can't use your legs
they're locked out from here
overhead and hip thrust full lockout
which people just lie yeah they'll add
100 lbs to their hip thrust cuz they'll
get it 80% of the way up and call that a
hip thrust yeah it it's very rare to get
a 12 times body weight total you get a
13 times body weight there's only one
person in that class so far yeah
and it's a cool thing because I think
that's probably the best thing you can
do for your physique is your relative
total on those six lifts and and
bodybuilders will say who cares about
when at max strength strength doesn't
matter it does matter for natural
lifters and yes you can get good good
physique from just doing lots of variety
and mind muscle connection and focusing
on slower tempos but in my opinion that
only gets you so far you've got to get
strong my girls with the best glutes are
very strong strong at hip thrust strong
at squats deadlifts I mean if I wanted
my PCS to get bigger at age 48 after all
these years of lifting guess what I
better build my bench I can't just get
there doing all the Flies and all all
the machines yes you can theoretically
increase volume but um there is you know
tension on the muscle is Paramount and
so you got to and not not not one rep
max but you got whatever you're set of
six you're set of 10 something you got
to be setting PRS and getting stronger
so anyway what I will say is like yeah
those power
lifts I started realizing well if you
wanted to get your deadlift as strong as
possible quit prioritizing the squad m
don't go for PRS do squats still but
don't try to progressively overload save
some gas save the the gas for the dead
list so what I started doing with booty
B Brett is I I had this rotating Focus
it's a periodization method I came up
with just for booty B Brett I wanted to
publish it in like a the method just B
like strength and conditioning Journal
because I think it's very um Innovative
so month one you prioriti is a
well-rounded month okay that you're you
know and we've changed it we've changed
it but the original Buddha peration was
a one month one it was a well rounded
month well in a well-rounded month guess
what you do Monday you squat Wednesday
you hip thrust and Friday you deadlift
so that works out well because you're
recovered for all of them squat hip
thrust deadlift and then bench chin up
military and then if you do three full
body days you're going to do a compound
upper body press a comound upper body
pull a squat a hinge and a Thrust so
five exercises per day for full body
body strength yep and then the abduction
for the upper and lower body are for you
throw those in because the psychological
everyone wants the upper body abduction
for the side delts the lower body
abduction for the upper glutes okay
so after this well-rounded month now
you've been pushing everything now it's
time to specialize month two is a squat
focused month so if you're trying to
build your squat all three full body
days can be the first lift can be a
squat pattern but one of them will
typically be some people can handle
squatting 3 days a week some people
can't why risk it people get Fai if they
squat deep people get knee pain low back
pain so have two squatting days like
Monday Friday squatting and Wednesday a
single egg a step up a reverse lunge a
Bulgarian split squat something like
that okay then what happens after the
squat focused month your knees are going
to be be feeling it a little bit so it's
a perfect time to transition to the hip
thrust okay so now you focus on the hip
thrust for a month every day starts out
with the hip thrust variation typically
it's barbell hip thrust on Monday
straight sets pause reps on Wednesday
bar plus band on Friday y or pulses or
something or one and a quarter reps but
two of the three are more focused on
lockout work yep now each one of these
months you're still going to do you're
still going to you're going to s squat
hinge and thrust every month that just
one is on the focus the others are on
the back burner okay and then what
happens at the end of the hypose month
you're feeling good again all right now
it's time for a deadlift month and then
you deadlifts you can't deadlift well
you can deadlift three times a week if
you do like stiff legs uh single leg RDL
and RDL but actual full deadlifts like a
Sumo or conventional or even a a trap
bar a semi- Sumo no but if you do that
have one Monday typically like say day
one Monday might be stiff leg or RDL
real strict light and stay stay a cou
sha failure Wednesday could be a hinge
still but it's a single legegg hinge and
then Friday is your heavy deadlift day
because you got two days to recover so
now after the four weeks of heavy
deadlifting guess what your low back is
taking a beating your overall system now
it's perfect time for a single legegg
month single legegg and dumbbell month
and that's what I love by definition
you're taking intensity out you're still
going to get Burns and you're going to
feel good but you're taking intensity
out because you you cut load down
because you're on a single leg period
and two Studies have shown one with
step-ups one of bulgarians should they
build squat strength just as well as the
bilateral lift yeah so you're still
keeping your strength up at minimum
you're going to keep M you're going to
maintain where you're at you're not
going to go backward you're going to
maintain you can even build so it's kind
of cool cuz some people like I grow my
glutes during the hip thrust month I
grow my glutes best during the single
egg month I grow my glutes during best
during the squat month maybe squats are
good for them or maybe it's because
during the squat month hip thrusts are
third and you're doing them with a mind
muscle connection who knows there's so
many moving Parts but there's it's more
fun train this way so that's how I did
Booty by Brett then I started talking
about you know what about bodybuilders
if we've been talking about this what if
you said Brett can you grow your delts I
just did it this year when length and
partials became popular I'm like I'm so
sick of doing dumbbell L raises I'm even
sick of cable lad I want to see if I can
grow doing length and partials and doing
uh basically more variety so I started
training delts three times a week and
they got bigger than they've ever been I
think and yes so some days I'm doing
heavy dumbbells Sometimes some some
sometimes cable but a lot of times just
doing the bottom partial and then I got
really scientific like how do you
maximally stretch this you really should
have the cable facing kind of this way
and just go to here and a dumbbell I
don't want to do sideline um but
basically I don't want to go all the way
up cuz after here there's no tension but
I would just lay on my side and just do
half halfway up yep length in
partials uh and and and just from the
greater volume I grew my delts you guess
what you get so sick of delt day you get
so sick of training your delts yeah so
yeah do it for a month but what if we
did that because maintenance is easy so
I made a video and I don't even know if
I ever posted it because it was the
sexual innuendos but I'm like imagine
having six balls and this is what
Progressive overload is but not just s
I'm saying six balls because each ball
represents my favorite lift yep my six
favorite for full body strength and
musculature and and even this earlier y
the six I lifted earlier listed earlier
so imagine trying to juggle six balls
it's really hard but what if every time
you gain strength you set a PR the ball
grew a little bit so each every time you
set a PR the ball gets bigger it gets to
a point where you can't juggle all six
of them they're knocking into each other
they interfere with each other and
you're you're you try to go up on six
lifts every month of your life you will
get nowhere no the balls will all fall
the ground and you stagnate you get
nowhere but what if you have six balls
laid out and you take two of them and
you're like okay and they get bigger
it's okay it's easy to juggle two balls
and these four on maintenance mode y
guess what the literature shows it's
very easy to maintain size and strength
with minimal volume so these four one
time a week one time a week of very
minimal sets week or even every other
week yeah so you can maintain your
strength and your size with lower so I
started thinking maybe we're doing it
wrong maybe the bodybuilders could have
seen better
results had they all had they switch the
focus from month to month so one month
you're doing body part so well I thought
about it one for upper one for lower
because what bodybuilder has ever had
prioritized glutes and glutes and
adductors go together because when you
go deep the adductors and deep deep hip
flexion actually have better leverage so
it's really really hard to do deep stuff
and not work your adductors because they
have such good leverage by the way are
the opposite uh what we're clearly
saying here is a
abductors verus abductors so the
abductors a BD were the jumping jacks
adductors are the ones that you're
pulling your leg close right together so
abductors add to the body abductors take
away right so what you're saying is in
Dr Magnus is a huge hip ex sensor down
deep right deep hip flexion so this your
growing muscle so if if you are
squatting say for example and you're
doing a lot or a lot of squatting type
of activities and say you only go a
quarter of the way down or halfway down
and then you change it and you go really
far down you're very likely to notice
really sore adductors right your groins
and this is exactly what you're talking
about because in that position they
start actually adding to hip extension
where in a in a the top position they
don't actually do that they have the
best leverage in deep hip was slightly
better than the glutes yeah um on
average which is why again you can train
your groin area if you want to think
about it that way by doing full range of
motion all the way to the bottom squats
if everything else works and you don't
have other issues with it you tremendous
you pair adductors and glutes together
so one month you're for the lower body
you're F focusing on glutes and
adductors one month you're focusing on
quads and one month hamstrings then the
other stuff goes on the back burner and
then for upper body it's hard to do all
of them because arms arms so I said one
month focus on pecs one month on the
back and one month on the delts what
about arms okay well then four months
and then I think you I think three
months of then you're back three months
then you're back so I thought about a
really effective system I was going to
start like Body by Brett to be for guys
but I don't know I don't know if I could
I'm I'm busy with Buddha but it's hard
anyway I thought that would be a fun
system and then I thought well instead
of having every person has their system
and they have all these theories you
know it would be how would you test that
well you'd have to do a few cycles of so
it have to be a nine Monon study you can
the control group do just
regular body part split training M and
then this new method where basically the
muscle you're prioritizing you're
training it three times a week y it's
hard to train chest three days a week
you
know quads three days a week it can be
done but that's the primary focus that
and then you have an upper body muscle
and then everything else goes on the
back burner goes on maintenance mode
would you see better hyper results
blasting and and cruising I don't know
it's just a theory but it's a it's a
strong Theory a strong argument could be
made yep I want to go back one thing to
um make sure we we finish the loop on
this one you mentioned uh what did you
call it the rule of three or something
like that what was the rule of thirds
exactly again what was that a third of
your exercises should be vertical in
nature vertical hip extension 1/3 should
be
horizontal and then 1/3 should be leral
rotary all right perfect okay great
thank you for that when you do that
interestingly when you do that it's not
just best for the glutes you also
because the vertical exercise are going
to hit the quads and the hammies the
horizontal will get some hammies too and
you know so it's like you're going to
get qu you you you or that or that
system I talked about where you pick a
squat lunge pick a hinge pick a Thrust
Bridge pick an Abduction the squat lunge
movements develop the quads and
adductors the hinge movements develop
the hammies and then so you get nice
devel it's a good system to use for
overall development if you want to
develop all the lower body of those
things okay um in your whatever it is
now 20 plus years of focusing on the the
hip thrust and the glutes and uh hip
extensions and all things kind of in
this
area I'm sure you've interacted and had
plenty of of people women are not come
up to you and say I've tried to grow my
glutes I've tried I've tried it's not
worked are there any themes that have
popped up over those years and those
interactions of kind of most common
mistakes that they've been making in
other words people have been like I've
been after this for a year it's not
working what am I doing wrong right yes
great question CU those types come to me
and they can get results it's really
hard for some people to get
stronger so when I when I talked about
the environment in glute lab like yeah
you show up to glute lab um yeah you're
you're not you're proud your because
you're the strongest person in your gym
cuz you hip thrust three plates per side
and then you come in you see you know in
in in Florida you see Dre you see via
you see Diane you see Masa you see all
these girls doing five plates per side
and you're like oh my God and not sloppy
reps that's the thing about I said 315
for 20 not sloppy reps you control it
full little slight pause at the top all
the way down all the way up rep 20 looks
a lot like rep one it's not like arching
and not not you know hyper extending
your spine and an tilting and only
getting 80% of the way up and jerking
the it's a smooth Tempo through a full
range of motion that is a great
indicator of someone who's going to have
amazing glute development but yeah um I
would say most people just can't get
strong without a trainer and I I will
tell you what fuels me cuz I travel
between Fort Lauderdale Las Vegas and
San Diego I was just in San Diego right
before this and they call it the bread
effect they say they independently came
up with it in Fort Lauderdale and in San
Diego and they just they Brett I don't
know what it is I I've been hearing this
for 20 years 28 years I can lift so much
more when you're around I don't know
what it is and I joke that it's my
fairmon oh absolutely but it's having TR
someone who trusts you you know hey I
want you go this this happened the other
day Lely she she's she's like uh warming
up she's hasn't ever deadlifted above
365 in training she hit 405 at a
competition then she had a back injury
and she's been anyway so I I just you
when you've coached for so long you know
so much just based off bar speed I don't
know what the bar speed actually is I'm
just watching you know what it looks
like so you have these indicators when
when I could watch my client Allegro
when I can watch le and I I watch go 275
and it goes Boop and she's just accelera
on the way up you can tell when it looks
like go you could have done that for 37
reps I go 35 she goes Boop I go you
could have done that for 37 reps okay I
don't know why I said 37 but I go she
goes what do I do next I go go 385 she's
like what go 3 don't don't warm up in
between I go what do you want to do she
goes I want to do whatever you tell me I
go then do
385 let's and then I announced it I'm
like everyone lely's going for 385 and
then Everyone's Watching and and then
you
know and and I always tell him with
sumo watch Stephy Cohen the bar doesn't
fly up y it doesn't rip off the ground
like convential take your time could
take four seconds for the plates but
that M you got to maintain good posture
you panic and you you round and you
shoot the hips up and now the lockout on
Suma becomes so infinitely harder so she
she pulls it she hits 35 puts down she's
so happy um this has happened for so
many years that it fuels me I love and I
love it too because when that when I'm
when I'm not around I so I travel back
and when I'm not around they don't go
for PRS when I am around they go for
they're like yay we can PR again yeah
and it's probably works out in my favor
because you don't want to crush them
every week right so it's great so you
train at my gym just because everyone's
so strong yeah like if you went if you
and I trained at some gym where
everyone's doing muscle ups and 20 like
we'd be like [__] I better do you can
probably do a muscle up I can't but
anyway never tried if everyone were
doing 20 pistol squats and I'm like I
can barely do a pistol Squad I better
get my ACT if everyone would do Nordic
ham curls like going up and down and
every person could do body weight
nordics for five reps and we'd be like I
can't even do one we'd be secretly doing
Nordic so a lot of it's to do with your
environment so these girls can't get
strong on their own they just don't know
what they're doing even you can tell
them that's why trainers have a job
that's why you know as of now personal
trainers have job security because it's
so hard to do on your own something's
wrong A lot of times it's the effort
they're putting forth they think they're
training hard but they could really do
five more reps if they really wanted to
at the end of the set a lot of times
they're sabotaging themselves because
God trainers around the world when they
hear this are going to be nodding their
head um men and women do both do this
they do it differently women will want
to combine and this will piss women off
if they hear this clip but they want to
combine weights with yoga Pilates spin
everything else and they'll say well why
why oh your heart isn't important your
heart health oh it's not important to be
flexible yes but uh you have to
prioritize so if you want hypertrophy
and you want glutes to grow and you're
doing all this extra exercise and you're
not really training when recovered and
you're not PRI you're not you're so busy
trying to fit in all your yeah six balls
in the air you're trying you got to you
got to train at the right time like
think about it make if if I said you
gota and you got to give yourself every
opportunity to PR what are you going to
do you're going to make sure you got a
good night of sleep you're not going to
go do an hour of cardio before you go
try and do that lift try to hit a bench
PR you're going to eat the right amount
just the right amount the right foods
that agree with you before your workout
the right time some people like to eat
an hour before some people like to train
fasted but like you're going to you're
going to show up feeling good you had
your pre-workout a half an hour before
your coffee or whatever makes you gives
you the best chance and that's what you
got to do day in and day out for lots of
years and what I see is when you're just
squeezing in your workout at the end of
the day when you're already stressed and
you have already and then you're just
going through the motions yep um you're
not going to grow like maximally you
might see some results and then two much
variety too much program hopping um
trying to do every exercise I love all
the exercises trust me in my gym for I
love quads and and hammies too so it's
hard because in my gym I've got H hack
squat machine the pendulum squat machine
leg presses Smith machine the V squat
like I've got it all what do I do you
know I I I want to hit quads sometimes
you're like I've been so distracted I
haven't done squats in a while and
you're going okay I got to get back to
squats oh I also have belt squats I have
all the and yeah they're all amazing and
they transfer to each other which is
cool but sometimes you take your focus
away same thing with hamstrings I've got
all every leg curl machine I've got
plate loaded 45 degree hyper
selectorized 45re hyper now you don't
even have to grab a dumbbell you just
hold on to something and pull the
reverse hyper you know I've got plate
loaded deadlift apparatuses the Hammer
Strength I've got the pit shark we do
still legs off that um and and and all
these gizmos too like our t-bell and on
the blocks are sliding leg for the
rolling the the the hammy track and
roller and all these cool things and you
can be
distracted because it's like you want
your hamstrings to grow try and get
really strong at stiff legs or you know
and then and then a leg seated leg crows
or something like so trust me I get it
but they're doing too much variety
they're not prioritizing Progressive
over
load and PRS and doing all the things
necessary to give themselves the best
chance of pring like adequate sleep
adequate protein adequate optimal
calories Etc um sometimes you'll you'll
go to women and and kind of try to gauge
how much protein they're taking in
sometimes it's like they're eating 50
grams of protein in a day and they weigh
120 and they see great results when you
take that
to 900 110 120 130 they see better
results that way like some people it's
like magic um so yeah got to get so
inadequate
protein um inadequate sleep and stress
levels program hopping but the most is
lack of effort yep and trying to make up
trying to compensate with effort with
volume and variety and it doesn't it
doesn't compensate for it you can't just
do all the exercises and doing 20 sets
with five reps in the tank probably
doesn't beat doing one awesome set to
True failure and riding it down in your
log book or on your app or in your notes
on your phone and then trying to beat it
because that requires a mental challenge
too when you know you've hip thrusted
315 for 15 and you're trying to get 20
and you're like how the hell am I going
to get 16 and S how am I going to get to
20 and then you know you're hip
thrusting tomorrow you're going to be
like okay I better eat optimally today I
better sleep optimally today and what
time am I going to train tomorrow I I
I'm going for 16 this is going to be
tough it's it's hard to do and it
doesn't always work linearly like that
it that's another complication so that's
why you have variety because yeah you
can't just go I got 15 16 then 17 then
18 then 19 then 20 usually you get 15
and then you take a big break and you do
all the things and then I'll send you
gear up for 20 again and it happens but
yeah that's another story today's
episode is sponsored by David David
makes protein bars unlike any I have
ever encountered they have an amazing 28
grams of protein only 150 calories and
zero gram of sugar that's right 28 gram
of protein and 75% of its calories come
from that protein this is 50% higher
than the next closest protein bar
honestly it's the best tasting protein
bar I've had by a mile while I often
talk about the importance of getting 1
gam of protein per pound of body weight
for things like muscle health and
recovery and the promotion of lean body
mass and say tidy the reality is that
for most people getting that one gram of
protein per pound of body weight is
really challenging however David makes
that easy their bars taste incredible
and are each packed with 28 gram of
protein I eat one almost every day and
always have two or three in my backpack
when I'm traveling like literally always
initially I was all about the blueberry
flavored one but these new peanut butter
flavors are just a cheat coat of yummy
it probably sounds funny but I eat them
as dessert all the time when you try
them you'll know exactly what I mean the
macronutrients one more time are 28 gam
of protein 150 calories and 0 gam of
sugar if you're interested in trying
these bars for yourself you can go to
davidpro
docomo again that's davidpro
docomo right and I would imagine that
many people are trying really hard but
their efforts are misplaced this is the
example of doing too many different
things so lifting maybe not lifting
frequently enough maybe not waiting long
enough it's only been a month right you
need probably several months or you're
adding in different forms of exercise
and things like that so you're trying
really hard your effort is super high
but there's not enough focus on stimuli
to drive that adaptation there's too
much distraction in the training right
another distraction you mentioned was
changing your programs too often right
so again this is where effort could be
high you could be really getting a burn
and really getting tired after the
workout but you did 50 different
exercises or you know you changed them
and because of that you probably
potentially did some maybe lower less
effective exercises your selection
wasn't great you were doing maybe all
body weight or all light bands and what
you're saying is you might be better off
picking one set of one exercise going
pretty heavy and then just getting out
of there right that would actually be a
a fun that would be hilarious to do like
a training study where you just have
them pick one set to go to F and then
you can do 15 sets we're not going to
track just do the Mind muscle connection
with those yep you know squeze feel the
squeeze feel the feel them the glutes
moving the weight but the that would be
a good system because it's hard
when you say progressive overload it's
hard to pin that down for people does
that mean do you go up on all four sets
yep do how do you go up another thing
that came to my mind here uh I don't
know how much you've experienced this or
not in terms of again let's think with
the same of I've tried to grow my glutes
um by the way I should interject here
we've been talking way more about the
glutes than I thought we were going to
today but you could change out glute for
anything else it doesn't actually matter
some of the details here do matter the
specific studies and the research and
and I'm going to ask here in a second
about how the glutes are are different
from other muscles but I hope what
you're gleaning from this is not just
only if you're sitting here thinking I
don't care that much about glutes or
whatever this is scientific principles
this is how do you answer research
questions this is specific and precision
right so you're talking about not all
exercises are the same not all muscle
groups are the same we've dug in on the
glutes so again the answers might be
different but this is exactly how you
should go about answering it if you care
more about the triceps or the quads or
the Cals or anything else so this is a A
system that you developed over you know
again almost 30 years now that can be
applied to anything else so I really
hope that people listening um are are
gleaning this out of it and going okay
maybe you do don't have some variation
of love for the glute but this is really
the Nuance that goes into to getting
better results for a very specific
question uh that you've really you know
formulated a careered out of so hope
that that message is coming through now
that said um the question on this last
particular topic is again I'm training
hard I'm trying to glow grow my glutes
but mine aren't growing I'm eating
protein I'm doing all those other things
off the field it's not hormones like how
does one at home whether they're a
trainer a coach or the actual person how
do you go about figuring out which of
these variations work based on your body
type and and what are the things I
should be thinking about and paying
attention to before I then throw an
exercise out and I I can say things like
okay great a new study came out it did
show that the let's just say goblet
squat is not as effective for glowing
the glutes as a barbell High bar back
squat is but I did the high bar back
squat for six months and I got nowhere
like how do I go about that system of
figuring out what works for my mechanics
and my physiology that's such a great
question um I know I used to do EMG on
all my clients and then and just to
clarify you said this in multiple EMG is
uh where we can go and directly measure
the muscle Activation so electrical
signals for muscle Activation so go back
as you've heard Brett say that a bunch
of times what he's saying is direct
measure of muscle activation yep
continue on now the problem with EMG for
estimating hypertrophy it does a good
job of of measuring activation the
neural portion of it the active portion
but not the passive portion the stretch
and which is another way of saying just
because a muscle is activated it doesn't
necessarily mean it's going to grow yeah
um there's some cross there clearly well
think about this because the I feel like
the long length got carried away away
for a while and it was all about
stretching and long length that's been
the trend in 2024 was all about it was
the year of longer muscle lengths yep
over a full range Motion versus pendulum
get can swing too far think about this
there are numerous studies that show you
can stretch a muscle and it will grow
pure stretch pure stretch now when you
stretch a muscle yes you probably get a
a little bit of activation just from
like protection and guarding but like
it's mostly all just passive y you're
just stretching it you're not activating
it and it grows through purely passive
mechanisms you can also just slap muscle
electrodes on and and activate a muscle
without stretching it and it grows EMS
and that's something that I was
skeptical about years ago and now the
have you looked at the research on this
over the years I have a catalyst suit
it's awesome yeah so fantas it grows
muscle yeah just activating the muscles
through muscle stimulation now if you're
doing a program Like Booty by Brat where
you're covering all your bases should
you do EMS on the side should you be
stretching a muscle can all muscles grow
through stretch what if I wanted to
stretch my delts what do I do I can't
I'm I'm blocked uh you could stretch
your W fem but can you stretch your
vases enough so when people talk about
stretch I'm like okay hammies yes pecs
yes calves yes yeah not every muscle I
think could benefit and then but like
with with that system I told you about
earlier putting muscles on the back
burner when if you did the prior the
rotating Focus that would be a good time
to say all right I'm going to slap
electrodes on the other muscles that I'm
not prioritizing oh there you go keep
the maintenance mode right and and help
add to the stimul because there's
there's a lot of research showing that
EMS grows muscles the first time I did
the Catalyst suit I got so sore now part
of it was cuz I pegged it like I just
went literally to the the end of the
contraction capacity and did like a 30
minute thing on it and got so that's
where it's activ on the way and you're
fighting you're moving stand there right
I'm like standing there basically
wearing a full body yeah a t unit
basically right it's over there and it's
like everything is squeezing and I just
like went to the wire I'm like squeeze
as hard as you can for 20 minutes and
turns out that's a lot of muscle
contraction and I got sore everything
yeah so user error on that it wasn't
user it was I knew what I was getting
into so so that's muscle growth through
activation and no stretching no passive
so n yeah clearly there are more
multiple that to me shows that there
have to be there has to be multiple
mechanisms leading to Ram leading to
muscle growth so there has to be a
mechanism that's more passive and a
mechanism that's more active because
there's separate stimuli so this is an
awesome question um I will just mention
briefly that I measured muscle
activation back in the day with all my
clients and I learned so much with
different people like I had this client
Sammy she could do squats with 285 PBS
back squats but if she did a goblet
squat with 50 and 70 pounds she got more
glute activation you're moving through
the same range of motion though so how
could that GL activation with a 20%
something with her about having the load
so then say with a deadlift if she had a
barbell she could do 225 lb or I think
might might have went up to 315 and then
she did U 106 lb kabell and a 203 lb
kabell and something about having the
loads centered more she just activate
her glutes a lot higher not everyone is
like thatly measuring her muscle her
glute activation glute activation in
different areas it was the same with a
50 lb goet squ go which traditionally
should activate the glut less because
it's a front load and Squad and all that
well something about load being centered
makes it I think I think when you have
kind of like lanky and you're folding
and you don't have the best squat for
you're battling buttwink you're battling
having a keep a neutral spine you might
have things shutting off and stuff you
know we can't always assume uh anyway I
had this girl Aaron at the same time and
she started doing all this uh well she I
I put bands or I how to do band seated
hip abduction and I'm like okay this is
activating all the are even leaning
forward even getting your lower glute
Max you're getting as high of activation
doing these than you higher than doing
one rep max squats well how many one rep
max squats can you do per week versus
band seated hip abduction so I showed
her the results like I said you're
getting higher band activation like
higher activation on bands than anyone
I've ever seen I think you should do
bands every day a lot of band will get
raed so she got carried away I
eventually starts bringing 20 different
bands to the gym I made a post on the
crazy band lady but her glutes grew a
ton so when you have these
individualized
prescriptions I think you can see better
results but but basically I don't have a
system for that the only thing I would
try is a long length Focus twice a week
so I'd say look you've been doing
something like booty B Bret let's switch
to two days and let's focus on glute
dominant squats box low Bar Box squats
sitting way back to parallel vertical
Shin the shin doesn't have to be
vertical but it's as vertical as
possible while still feeling right and
then glute dominant step UPS bulgarians
lunges meaning like not not a knee
dominant not an upright letting your
knee go Way Forward keeping the shin
pretty vertical leaning and then and
then rdl's
and let's do those good morning rdl's uh
let's do these exercises for a while but
hit them hard but just twice a week see
if you grow better from that you're
going to know within a couple of months
Y and then if that doesn't work let's
try a short length Focus let's do four
or five days a week we're only doing hip
thrust and bands I did this with my
client Beth Beth did powerlifting but
she had a coach that was all about the
powerlifts and I said if you were
focused on hip thrust no my coach hates
them have you ever done band work no he
thinks those are wimpy too all right
just do hip thrust and band work for
like six months and do them as
frequently and as much as you can see
how that works and her butt blew up yeah
blew up so when all these people are
like she was G she was strong at squats
and deadlist they weren't working for
her and so you'll hear so many anecdotes
and these scientific people I could call
them all out right now these scientific
people and they don't care about otes
and that's and to me they're not
scientific cuz you can say look at this
person they will just shut it out well
that doesn't mean anything what if she
wasn't doing squat okay I'll show you a
video of her squats in deadlist she had
good form what do you say then like they
just don't want to reconcile the to they
want to stick to one you know one rigid
method and you got to be flexible if you
want to be a good personal trainer so
that method worked better for her so I
would do the two extremes two days a
week of of long length glute work versus
like 5 days a week of shorten position
glute work yeah it could be a genetic
reason or just anatom you tolerate these
because if you if you don't tolerate an
exercise well and it gives you pain or
fear inhibition you're not going to
maximally activate your glutes so anyway
maybe they frequency versus like some
people respond better frequency some
people even your your Anatomy what if
your moment arms are terrible in the
stretch for glutes and really ideal and
and I also think you can change through
training when you do concentrics or
shorter lengths you will lose sarir in
series when you do Ecentric or longer
lengths you will add circom mirors in
series so maybe you can change the way
even and that might affect neural
activation too the muscle says this m
we've we've we've caused this muscle to
be more effective at longer lengths or
more effective at shorter lengths and
there could be we just don't know enough
right now and that's what always
frustrates me about social media right
now it's rewarded these bold claims uh
camps where you're very strong like this
is the method this is what yields the
best muscle growth it doesn't reward
uncertainty it doesn't reward
scientific claims or cautious claims
evidence based as well I get mad because
I'm like if I don't know the answer to
this like then you don't know the answer
to this you know because no one does the
mo researches this stuff as much as me
and I see these people making these bold
claims like we don't have the evidence
for that yet we don't know when we need
there's so many studies deep squats
versus squats Sumo versus there's not
one training study on Sumo versus
convential hip should you do full range
should you do partial should you use
bands should you you know there's we
don't have we need we need like 30 glute
studies to be able to speak confidently
about what works best until then it's
theoretical and we should be cautious
about what we think we know what do you
think about a system I just sort of jot
It Down based on what you're
saying um checkpoint number one if
you're trying to grow your glutes and
whatever exercise you're doing whatever
your program design is it's resulting in
pain uh not muscle soreness but pain uh
your back is going hurt your knees hurt
right then pretty obviously stop that
don't do that right so the checkpoint
you could run through in your head is if
in your program you're then getting
injured whether we mean like a true
injury or is just simply the kind of
pain you don't want yeah then we need to
change your program that seems to be
like a pretty intuitive first start so
don't why you don't need be in pain and
then two this would be the consistency
play we're going to lose training volume
y over time yep after that and this is
where like I just sort of made this up
the second thing I would think about in
my head is is the actual
exercise feeling like it's working um
how much credit do you give or not
should people feel their glutes working
in the workout um I'm sure it doesn't
have to be 10 out of 10 but if if I'm
doing hip thrust and I don't feel my
glutes getting a pump if I don't feel
them getting
tired um should I be concerned that
that's not working for me or am I okay
there so let me let me play Devil's
Advocate and then tell you what I really
think we imag we looked at that in the
Plotkin study uh 2023 Daniel Puck and
the researcher asked everyone which
exercise do you feel your glutes more in
Hip thruster squats all 20 some subjects
said hip thrust and they they grew the
glutes the same they were equal well so
but I do think it is because yeah if you
don't feel your glutes much in hip
thrust it's probably not the best
exercise for you or you should find a
way a variation way of carrying it out
or like maybe you like the Smith machine
more maybe you like maybe you feel
position you're feeling it too much in
your quad H how could that not help yeah
that's always been a thing when the
since the dawn of bodybuilding try to
feel it and every person tweaks there F
figures out a way to feel it more that
has to help yep but it's but it's also
when I was getting the advantage of
being a bro we wanted to get strong you
know when we're in college and we're
like everyone's stronger than you you're
like wanting to get stronger we weren't
focused on feeling my delts during a
military press you know what I mean I
just wanted a stronger should press yeah
and guess what you get really strong
with pretty good form and everything
develops and that's the argument I hear
both sides of the argument the people
will say oh tell me how you do a squat
without activating your glutes but come
on I can like I mean when you're walking
up stairs be super
upright and you'll feel your quads more
and then lean in and like let the hips
come up a little more and you'll feel so
much more glute walking upstairs you
can't tell me technique doesn't matter
no it does and we saw that in our our uh
our trap bar versus conventional
deadlift study right so the aggregate
results are different than the
individual results yes because some
people when they did a trap bar deadlift
actually kept the exact same position
that they did in their conventional
deadlift others went super vertical it
was basically like a leg press they're
standing straight up where their
deadlift they were much more so guess
what happened with EMG activity on
average no difference cuz it washed out
yeah right but the individual person
depending on their arm length primarily
right that allowed them to stay in the
same position or not yeah it completely
changed so for some of our participants
in that study the trap bar deadlift was
way more quad activation but for others
it literally changed nothing whatsoever
between conventional and Brad shield and
I did a rear rear delt study the first
EMG study he did he just got his nuraing
unit yeah and we wanted to see what's
better neutral or pronated grip cuz back
then Ione said it's not pronated won't
grow your rear ads oh yeah well neutral
grip on average outperform it but there
were huge inter inter individual
difference some people getting way
Higher One Way versus the other so go
with what you feel the most because if
you're moving a muscle through the same
range of motion and getting similar
stretch then the the the technique that
activates it the most in my opinion well
but sometimes that technique can
influence the stretch yep so under under
the same all right if passive tension is
equal then the higher active tension
wins out yep but you can't have a
technique that
increases while decreasing passive and I
think that's the argument for Sumo Deads
well it gets you less stretch but it
gets you more activation in a lot of Cl
a lot of clients a lot of studies not
there's only one study by esam looking
at EMG with sumo versus convential and
they showed similar activation in the
glutes but there's probably 12 studies
at this point on squats and other exas
in Sumo in general you get greater glute
activation but you're going to get
lesser glute stretch so there needs to
be a training study yep and then we need
to see for ourselves but right now
people should just be cautious they
should say I prefer conventional because
you get a little bit better stretch um
maybe you know but but don't be like
Sumo is all adductor and zero glus
Maximus sumo's got to be the dumbest
thing ever cuz then you get all the
ticktockers and all the they repeat your
stuff and then it becames fact before
we've ever even looked into it yeah so
okay back back to my list here of of
kind of five things number one start off
don't get in pain two um hopefully you
feel something either in the muscle
you're trying to train that day or
potentially some amount of soreness the
next day obviously we know that more
sore is not better feeling it getting a
pump getting sore these are indicators
that you worked the muscle though seems
reasonable if you're not in pain you're
feeling it even getting a huge pump on
the day and you're still not growing
then potentially think about going heavy
a general problem people have had you've
sort of mentioned this earlier is they
don't realize that hey you know three
set to 50 with the band like that may
not be the jam to grow every muscle
right you may have to Progressive
overload Progressive overload right my
gut is most people will be done by by
this one in terms of you're going to
start growing at this point but let's
say I got that box check focus on my
muscle now focus on potentially
frequency frequency right so now I've
done I'm not in pain my glutes are
getting pumped I'm going really heavy
I'm at 315 whatever the numbers are now
maybe think about adding in that extra
day volume frequency you could kind of
play what like one game here right sure
um so those would be kind of like four
and five volume or frequency so maybe
you need to add another day with those
less damage
ones so this is where more bands could
come in y it's just a way of getting you
more volume sure um but how does that
kind of like five step checklist
progression sound for somebody
struggling a reasonable approach there
is there anything else you would add to
that I I would say have a one in there
where you really focus on mind muscle
con activation yep somewhere in there
saying what if cuz there's evidence
there's evidence that it makes brain
changes in the cortical the re the the
motor cortex there's a couple there's at
least one maybe two I think there's a
recent one too showing that you get
actual changes in the brain responsible
for activating that mus so maybe if you
have a little month where you focus on
mind muscle connection not even going to
f with squeezing the [__] out of the
muscle and really trying to Target in
your brain you know in that study they
look these bands and it was isometrics
because I thought isometrics would build
greater brain changes cuz you're
focusing hard that might make a
difference yeah interesting okay so
making sure that again if those
progression strategies aren't working
that you're just trying to be more
connected directly to the muscle those
connections more right and getting more
out of it um makes a a ton of sense uh
We've we've gone on quite a journey thus
far I got a couple things uh if you've
still got some energy left I could go
for hours I know I I know you can um to
finish up on so um one of them is the
very first question I asked you is how
do you think about training men like
versus women and you laid out a lot of
stuff to think about I just want to
double tap on them if I can one uh
relating to
recovery um and so I'll ask this from
the scientific
perspective as well as and potentially
even more important your years of
experience so what do we understand
about men versus women in the context of
strength training here regarding things
like recovery um have you truly seen
that women recover more than men on
General uh do they need more volume
those are like kind of two separate
questions and then a third one I'll
smuggle in here is are there any other
things physiologically like menstrual
cycle phase or things like that that you
have found to either be big
considerations or things you put a lot
of effort into and then Pann out to not
really matter too much awesome um yes
yes and yes so but but also so it could
be that the women are on a permanent
specialization program glutes Booty by
bread is a glut specialization plan it's
not a glute only but it's a
specialization full body with like we we
hit quads adductors and hammies but we
don't do a ton of leg extensions seated
hip adductions or leg curls because that
would just take away from what you could
potentially recover from with the glutes
you can't just hit every M what if you
trained every muscle like you did with
booty B Bret we do where you did 36 to
45 sets a week of glutes of with quads
with hammies with adductors calves qu
you it's too much you could never
recover so it's maybe they I just think
they can recover better because they're
on a glute specialization because they
have reduced volume of the upper body
muscles and even the quads and handies
and you've intentionally as you said
earlier built in a day that is a more
recoverable day so the exercise
selection by default is easier to
recover from so yeah so but I but I
don't think it's just that early on in
my training career I'm like man these
women can do these workouts they K I
tried to do one once 2007 tried to do
what I give my girls I was on the ground
laying there for a half an hour I was
like is it possible to have a heart
attack at at 28 go 30 31 or two or
something I'm like and I remember just
sitting there like wow that made me gain
respect for what I put them through so
it could be the influence of hormones
and estrogen and they have bigger type
one fiber hypertrophy they have higher
estrogen maybe that leads to better
muscle damage repair if you put a guy
through the workouts they do it it kills
them and but the girls can bounce back
quicker uh I know there was a study I
read back in the day on bench press guys
who would take um two or three days to
uh get back like say they did a one rep
max or or uh took them two days to
repeat that the the women could repeat
that the next day and you could say well
that's cuz they're not as strong
relatively but with women they are as
strong with a lot of these glute
exercises as men relatively they're
stronger relatively women are stronger
at hip thrust than men and again you
could absolutely yeah almost absolutely
as well you could say well that's just
because they do it a lot too but I think
there might be something with the
anatomy but anyway I think they can do
more volume I think they can recover
slightly quicker so their programs can
be a little more you think they need
more volume in other words if do would
they have the same effect if they were
given the same amount when I when I
train okay do they need more
volume I think the better question is
what's is is there a different optimal
volume for them for hypertrophy I do
think it would be slightly shifted
upwards for women compared to men but
not double you know it might be that for
men hypothetically speaking say
12 sets was optimal for a muscle group
for a man whereas maybe it would be 16
for a woman but but also we talked about
earlier it depends every answer is it
depends you have the people who can
recover better than others and who push
themselves harder too you have the
people who there's also some weird thing
about Tempo like you have those people
who like on chinups you
like and you're like okay they're done
so
they do another rip and you're like and
then they get three more and you're like
what how I cuz I'm done like people
always go wow you had three more in the
tank and I'm like no I was I wouldn't
have gotten one more it just looks like
that because I'm a very explosive lifter
I either explode up or it don't won't go
up at all but anyway I'm the same as you
for the record so some of those people I
think the the more grinder you are
that's tough to recover those are harder
to recover from than the um but anyway
there's a lot of factors that play with
but it's how hard you push yourself
versus your muscle damage and Recovery
genetics yep I so I do think they can do
a little more volume and a little more
um like what's optimal volume and
frequency for them is slightly higher
they don't seem to get as damaged and
beat down they seem to get beat down
from trying to juggle too many forms of
exercise too many things they tend to
want to jam-pack their schedule and
they're like and I don't know if men are
I'd be curious to see if modern day men
are like that cuz me I'm kind of like I
don't want to plan as many things you
know but anyway I I think that that adds
to their stress and but if if they had
no stress in their lives in that way
they could recover even better um but
and and their relationship stress they
are they care so much about their
relationships it really weighs on them
so anyway there are a lot of different
factors and I'm probably going to get
some stuff for that comment cuz whenever
you say that differences between men and
women you get in trouble and I'm like
man I could never raise a kid not on my
own like a woman can I could never do
half the stuff they can do and
multitasking they seem to be better at I
have so much respect for a lot of my
women I could not do what they do I
could never do life is so hard and then
you add a kid to the mix and then you
had two kids and you're breastfeeding
and you're getting woken up at night I
don't know how the hell they do it so I
have the utmost respect but I think
there are definite differences and we
shouldn't try to be the same as with
regards to training the biggest
differences are goal related the
physiological differences I think are
worth mentioning like you said I think
they recover faster can handle a little
more volume and then you said the third
qu piece wasal cycle menal cycle so
train differently during during
different phases of ccle so this this
research got popular and then Lauren
coleno simple came around and just
squashed it I love it cuz I was like
you're going to get she was in my lab
you know that yeah she's great she she's
awesome
yeah and and and but but here's the
deal on on average strength doesn't
fluctuate that much throughout the
menstrual cycle Etc but does on the
individual level just what you talked
about with the trap bar deadlifts I have
women that are especially if they're not
on birth control and when they it's
crazy because a lot of women the day
their period starts they're they're
weakest but some are they're strongest
at that point and I'd be like like I had
this client Comm in Phoenix and I'd be
like did you start your period today and
then she's like how'd you not cuz you
just crush your deadlift PR every time
she would start her period She was a
monster other women don't even want to
train when they start especially hip
thrust they don't want pressure on their
abdomen you got to know these things you
have to be aware of them and be
sympathetic to it because everyone's
different some are stronger some are
weaker some don't want to be there they
don't want to train so you bargain with
them you say oh you you you start your
period you don't want to hip to us don't
hip thrust let's do Kickbacks let's do
this give them stuff that doesn't feel
bad so at least they make it in the gym
and they feel good about themselves but
yeah these These are factors that men
don't have in their lives and don't have
to think about it it's an additional
variable with women and it definitely
matters on the individual level because
some women get so nauseous so irritable
they don't even want to we don't have to
deal with that that is a factor that
should be considered um in your in your
program design but just on a personal
coaching level personal level not a
group LEL I don't change my programs to
to to reflect that but in person I
definitely change things up if it if if
the person is has really bad periods or
period cramps and emotions associated
with it you absolutely have to change
things up yeah so a factor to pay
attention to but perhaps no set rules
that should be automatic based on
generic cycle phases you look at I
wonder if I think Lauren's research
would agree with that for the most but I
wonder if hormones changed are unique
because you look at the graph and it's
like here's here's testosterone here's
estrogen here's progesterone and then
you look at like
premenstrual of course progesterone is
highest I think and then estrogen
testosterone lowest of course like or
like right it makes sense that that
would you'd be your weakest there but it
doesn't on a group level maybe hormones
are different depending on the person
too that's the thing I also will tell
you that like my girls um
are my San Diego Squad is all natural
right
um my Florida Squad most are all natural
they're very but I always tell them like
when girls get mad when I say all
natural they'll be like they have breast
implants that's not what all natural
means that's not what all natural means
in our world Natty means you don't take
gear you don't take anabolic steroids
yeah you don't take sarms you don't take
peptides I don't even think peptides
really are a factor now
depending right so I'm so close with
these ladies I've been training them for
seven years in groups when you train
women in groups they talk it's like I'm
it's like I'm a a the gay friend but I'm
not gay that's how I get treated they
will talk about they will talk about
anything in front of me because they're
very comfortable so I hear everything
and and they'll be like coach my my
testosterone levels came back it's at 14
and I'm like and I'm like okay like you
you're super horny that's all you talk
about is sex and you're strong as hell
you can deadlift you know 385 you think
you have a 14 testosterone level check
it again yeah but enough of them came
back I swear like my average
testosterone level of my clients is like
not even 20 it's like probably in the
teens how they're strong as hell I start
to wonder
if really intense training lowers
women's testosterone levels because
Normal is 6 to 90 for women that's a 15
fold difference but you think some of
these girls they have these amazing
physiques can I get someone in the 40s
or 50s or 60s yeah no one's at a 90 yeah
but they're in the te a lot of things
going on there they're in the teens so
yeah that's a whole other thing that I'm
would love to look into is if should we
be periodizing to let their testosterone
come up or anything because I'm like or
maybe that they're all just getting
false readings cuz these places are
lying to them to try to get them on trt
cuz I'm in a constant battle saying you
don't need trt look at you you look
amazing um so yeah okay well thank you
those are really good insights uh that's
a question that is that comes up a lot
and there's the research on that that's
great people can interpret that but it's
always interesting to hear perspective
of somebody who's you know been in the
trenches with people trying to get as
strong as they can trying to grow muscle
and seeing how that um played into your
coaching and I think that was a very
helpful answer and I know a lot of
coaches and a lot of individual people
are going to go okay great now I have
freedom to yes take the best option for
me depending on where I'm at um one last
real technical question here and then I
got a couple more uh but the technical
one is regarding the glutes versus other
muscles right uh you've mentioned this
several times now but I want to make
sure this was really clear because I
thought it was really
helpful we talk about training as if all
of our muscles respond to training the
exact same way right and so this much
intensity this much load this much
frequency this is how you progress but
have there been any themes over your
career that you've noticed about the
glutes as a collective
musculature um that are you know
significantly different than the delts
or the triceps or the Ping like that
anything to jump out of either maybe
things to do or things not to do that's
special about the glutes
I just think they're more simple a lot
of a lot of muscles are
simpler because well what what I like is
comparing the glutes to the delts Yep
they're both ball and socket joints you
know um a lot of movement lot of range
of motion around them but delts you have
three subdivisions y an middle and
lateral and it's you really Target One
Division over the other so when you talk
about delt volume when you train any
upper body pressing move M be it
dips um decline flat push-ups bench um
incline shoulder press be the neck press
every one of them will
train the anterior delts and then going
out in the expanding out in the frontal
plane more uh is going to activate the
the middle delts a lot the side delts
but not rear delts don't get super high
on pressing but then the rear delts get
do get activate during all the row all
the pulling motions from pull Downs to
angled pull Downs to rows um to even you
know even rows upright like more upright
so the rear delts will get the rear dels
will get activated with a lot of pulling
movements so they can handle a lot of
volume because you can also add in
isolation movements but you if you
wanted to you could do three sets of
reared out raises three times a week if
you really wanted to you could do three
sets of laterals three times a week with
variety you could do three sets of front
raises three times a week and you could
be doing presses and pulls so they can
handle a lot of volume the delts can but
they do you know they do you know
shoulder flexion abduction you know and
then like they shoulder extension and in
different planes too and different
angles and stuff so so they're very
versatile muscle group when you look at
the glutes the the glutes aren't just
the glute it's the glute Max the glut me
the glut Min and it they carry out hip
extension abduction extra rotation
poster pelvic tilt but also poster
pelvic tilt should just be thought of as
like short Arc hip hip
hyperextension um but anyway uh like you
can bend over in the and do abduction in
the in the transverse like being being
knees to chest
abduction versus upright versus leaning
back like frontal plane so they do a lot
they do several different joint actions
and then you can vary The Exorcist to
work more in the stretch position to
stretch you more to work the stretch
more to squeeze you more to to have more
hip hyperextension to work more in the
stretch
position it's complicated but it's just
how complicated you want to make it it's
like for glutes okay just get really
strong at uh bulgarians Romanian I and
hip thrusts and you're going to have
pretty good glutax development and throw
in some ABD do some lateral band walks
three times a week to warm up and you'll
be fine but no there's more to it okay
well let's let's think of other muscles
quads well it's so simple it's a it's
it's pretty much just a the knee is a
hinge joint all right just get really
strong at either any one of these or a
variety of them but I would say they all
probably build the quads very
effectively the first is
squats uh and probably high bar even
better heel elevated even better front
squats High bar squ whatever but get
strong at squats you're probably going
to have nice quads but now add in hack
squats or uh or pend the pendulum squat
or belt squats or leg press in a quad
dominant fashion how can you not have
big vases but what about the rec fem
it's a two-joint muscle if you want to
maximize Rec fem development you now you
need need to add in a leg extension type
movement a single joint well so you add
in leg extensions but leg extensions are
even better when you lean back they're
probably even better when you stress the
stretched position that's on like that
Prime machine that really you can change
the load if you have a plate loed that's
just pure plate load the Titan yeah then
you're only working the squeeze I
actually like to do that because I'm
like everything we do works the
stretched position um I like working the
squeeze position but anyway you could
also do [__] squads or you could do
reverse
nordics um and you maybe you need to do
some hip flection to to maximize Rec fem
growth but it's not as not quite as
complicated as as the glutes yep
hamstrings can be complicated because
there's a lot of studies hamstrings
there's a ton of research on because of
hamstrings strain injuries injuries
right and these range from EMG to it's
my favorite muscle for the record and it
is the one I think people train the
least and should train more of yes
because completely underrated foot
position like with leg extensions
doesn't seem to alter vasty recruitment
but it does for hamstrings uh bo knee
pain and other foot injuries and back
injuries man hamstrings like people just
don't train them so you have knee
flexion movements and you have hip
extension movements with hip extension
you could go squeeze position with back
extensions um like loaded you know 45s
and back extensions and and and uh you
can go
um in knee flexion you can work them in
a stretch with seated hamstring so with
seated hamstring curls you should be
leaning forward if possible or just at
least as upright as possible don't be
leaning back you want as much stretch
but also make sure that pad is down far
and you make sure it's working you all
the way up into full knee extension so
you're getting the maximum stretch um
but then you can do lying leg curls
kneeling leg curls and they all seem to
work different maybe like slightly
different areas variation is a good
thing for hammies okay calves calves are
probably the simplest exercise to train
because what we're finding is seated Cal
raises don't appear to add to the mix
and neither does the squeeze position
yeah like there are now a few studies
showing that calves almost don't even
need to come up all the way you can just
do the stretch position but all but if
you do come up all the way extend the
set with some length in partials or just
do more sets but yeah if you just want
to do you
know a quick three sets of C raises uh
you know just do standing you don't need
to do seated that tends to it seems to
build the Solus just the same and uh the
seated is going to make it hard for your
gastrock to get involved at all it's
going to basically be zero right on the
seat the calf Ray yeah so seated been
shown to not um it it doesn't add to to
the equation when you're doing
straight-legged
um I don't think I've seen us like
donkey cry does that add I don't think
it does there is some evidence that
turning the toes in versus out can help
sure um but yeah like
basically uh the Cales are probably the
simplest muscle to train because just do
standing Cal raises work the stretch
position you're good to go Um can the
calves handle the Vol do you do you need
the variety in calves with do that you
can with glutes the C the like pretty
much you they just do plantar flections
so you don't really need so it's like
and then look you look at the pecs okay
there's the upper middle and lower
fibers if you just get strong at like
low incline press you probably get most
of your bang for your buck but then
you're like okay should I work all the
angles should I do weighted dips uh
should I do incline press what what
incline should I vary the incline should
I do 15 30 45 60 75 90 um obviously not
90 then 90 degrees would be mostly all
front delts but like what about now your
PEC isolation movements okay should you
do uh
flies or pec deck or Cable Crossovers
should you just focus on the stretch
just do dumbbell flies do you need to
come up all the way why you lose tension
just do length and part
okay well um so F do you need the
squeeze should you do crossovers focus
on the squeeze pack deck where you
really focus on I don't we don't have
enough research but to me it just makes
sense y it just makes sense to be strong
throughout a full range of motion and to
incorporate a lot of variety but we you
know it's like the more Divergent the
muscle the bigger the muscle and more
subdivisions the more complic and the
more joint actions the more complicated
it becomes do we need to does the
stretch help a lot they have better
moment arms like coming up all the way
how do you stretch the lats the most how
do you stretch the pecs the most um like
this re this scientist named um kasm
came out and said you you stretch the
pecs more with a um kind of like with a
45 degree arm angle right all right but
maybe what about when I do Guillotine
you know because you can lower the bar I
feel some of the fibers upper fibers
stretching more that way should we be
doing Guillotine work that doesn't agree
with some people's shoulders um and it's
like what about the lats okay how do you
stretch the lats the most he kasm would
say do a a cross arm crossbody motion
that might stretch the lats the most
arguably so but you know sometimes you
can have if you're big muscles you might
not get the full stretch your Anatomy
might your rib agage or for me I can't
seem to get over that much on these but
would it stretch my lats the most and
then you start altering your your um
spinal and your scapula and stuff and
all that and you can get a better
stretch and I think this stuff is very
important we should talk about it it h
it for what's optimal or not but what
happens is everyone starts focusing on
optimal optimal optimal and then they
the pendulum goes too far this way and
you have these nerds like ripping on Ben
over Rose and like weighted chinups and
stuff and like I I like it cuz it's
funny cuz interesting I contradict
myself I've always liked Sumo for
glutes compared to Conventional but I've
always liked superpad narrow for lats
compared to wide grip oh yeah and it's
like but I'm not consistent because I'll
say well superate stretch you more but
wide grip activates a little bit more in
my opinion for lats you should probably
do some stuff in the frontal plane some
stuff more in the Sagal plane some stuff
that goes full overhead in the full
stretch even though the lats don't have
good moment arms or activate here that
much you should just always use a
variety yes some muscles CU see with the
lats you've got different divisions
upper middle lower and how do you build
maximize the size of each and it's
like I like analyzing everything geeking
out on the biomechanics just don't let
it take away from like the basics and
like getting strong at the basics
because yeah if you look at like the way
Tom plats trained his quads he was an
animal he got super strong at squats and
hack squats he'd go he didn't go down he
turned the hack Squad into a [__] Squad
yeah and these leg extension you're
seeing him like flying up on these leg
extensions screaming and go he'd go
until he'd do he was doing length and
super sets 30 years before they were a
thing like before they were popular it's
that intensity but yeah he had the
greatest quad development of all time
they're absurd and that was before they
were even now now you see since then
tell me a body part that's bigger on a
guy 30 years ago then yeah today only
plats with his legs his qus yep that's
it um okay awesome that was really
really really helpful um last thing I
want to get from you here is you know I
was telling you this before we started
you're you're a unicorn in the field for
many reasons one of which is I think
you're one of the very few people
who I really respect and enjoy who has
actually built themselves it's not fair
but mostly on a single brand right so
this is your company names this is your
your exercise equipment your Instagram
your social media is the glute guy right
you despite the fact you have a PhD
and you've done all the things we talked
about earlier you've pushed into a
single brand and why that matters is how
do you handle that then when research
comes out and it says your brand maybe
isn't great right so another words what
I'm saying is if you were to be the the
the lemon juice guy and then all of a
sudden research comes out and says hey
lemon juice is actually not great for
you and like oh my God what do you do
your your career like
this has happened many times in your
career right there have been many many
studies come out that as you talked
about earlier have countered maybe what
you've thought before and I think you've
done such a beautiful job over the years
of being so overt so honest with that
you're the first guy I hear about when
new studies come out on the hip thrust
that show negative results not because
you're criticizing the study like if if
that is true of the study you bring that
up but rarely do you do that almost
always it is a
hey guys updating our thinking here
turns out I had this idea it doesn't
work anymore um now looks like that's
not the case and this is sort of how we
modifying it so what what I'm the
question that I'm eventually smuggling
in here
is how have you handled that how do you
think about that and then
secondarily what are the most
known criticisms of the hip thrust what
has been shown scientifically what is it
not good at what is it limited in what
are the downsides um because I don't
want this entire discussion to feel like
just a big you know Glu great are
great and I don't mind bringing this up
because you have done this more than
anybody in your career about what looks
like sabotaging your own brand but to me
it's only elevated you even more because
when you do say things that are positive
about the hip thrust I feel like you
generally give a fair representation of
literature and you don't run away from
when things don't support your brand so
um what do we know about the the
downside there's no really cons that's
probably not a there's no negatives of a
hit thrust but what are the limitations
what are they not good at when is it not
the best choice and then how have you
handled that when that's happened in
your career and saving your brand if if
that's probably not a world that
resonates with you but you know yeah
great questions I I if I was the hip
drust guy yes I'm the guy who
popularized it if I was the hip drust
guy I'd be screwed cuz like well I don't
know if we had enough studies you're
going to find it's useful for some
things but it's not yeah then I'd be
like oh God I said this but being the
glute guy I just need to flow with the
research and what I want to do is be the
first to notify my people of a study so
if if no no one will care like and I
want to fund this I want to carry out
the studies CU then I'm the hero either
way yeah if I do a study on full squats
versus parallel
squats and for glute development for
glute development and full squats wins
all the Olympic weightlifters are like
hooray contas saves the day and then if
it's to parallel the powerlifters get to
say see suck at Olympic lifters we told
you um but that if if I yeah I the plot
can study meno henselman and I funded
that yeah 80 freaking Grand we spent of
our own money like 40 Grand each props
to meno
um we wanted lab too he's great yeah we
wanted MRI because we don't fully trust
ultrasound for glutes for other muscles
yeah but glutes It's Tricky so anyway I
was so glad that I got to present that
and helped be involved in that because
it was a needed study and I was wrong
now I was the first time what you're
talking about is with hip thrust with
speed development so the first study on
the topic was from my PhD thesis it
looked at adolescent um male rugby
players and it showed that front squat
led to Greater vertical jumps but hip
thrust led to better acceleration
improvements in sprinting and that was
in line with the force Vector hypothesis
right you want to jump higher put more
force on ground that way you want to run
faster put more force on the ground that
way it's common sense and
then you see this in the research kind
of like you see boom and then boom and
then with hip thrust it went back again
to here so the first study showed great
results so then a couple researchers
designed studies here's the deal um one
I know you got hammered on the force
Vector Theory eventually I got hammered
on and now it's like legit now it's yeah
it's back so the next couple of
researchers who studyed I got to look
back at these papers Chris Bishop was
one of them and there was one uh
a Chinese or Japanese baseball study uh
we we I think was the last but anyway um
like that baseball study showed that
like hip thrust grew grew the the
baseball player squats squat strength
just as effective as squats did and
that's what I found in one of my I did a
twin study and the hip thrust the the
the the hip thrust twin grew her squat
um like went from a 95lb squat to 135lb
squat without squatting just in six
weeks of hip thrusting and it was crazy
it was and it cleaned up her form too
like she hip
so but you look at those those couple of
studies I I want to look back at two
things I don't know why I don't know
this number one their Tempo if they're
doing like a 2 second up and 4 second
down that is the slowest hip thrust
known to man um people this is one of
the most the biggest things people are
wrong about in the industry is that
Tempo matters so much for hypertrophy it
doesn't look at a lot of these
bodybuilders are heaving away they're
using momentum they're exploding because
intuitively they know a lot of them were
doing like length and partials too just
doing bottom position stuff um they were
they're sometimes ahead of the C
sometimes they're dead wrong but
sometimes the Bros had it right anyway
there's people out there and they will
swear by it it's like a they think that
like the slower the tempo the better it
is for muscle growth and a review paper
by shonfeld and and uh creger I think
showed two to eight seconds led to the
same muscle growth but I'm telling I
think it's more than that by the way
it's I think it's like two to 15 like it
almost doesn't matter the only thing is
when you have like a 10-second
concentric there's I think there's only
one study on the super slow method I
think it was 10 seconds up 5 Seconds
down and that led to less growth but you
can get a variety of uh results but also
a new study on cheating momentum Brad
shonfeld did this study too and they
showed with like curls and I don't know
if it was tricep but basically heaving
away at curls versus very strict curls
and they had the same biceps grow
yeah so the strict people can say h this
is what I love about presenting the
research cuz you're the champion the
strict people get to say see you went
lighter used less load and got the same
muscle growth and it's safer clearly
it's going to be safer you have less
injuries and the heaving crowd can say
see you went heavier heed away you're
probably going to grow other muscles cuz
you're using some front delt and some
connected tissue development and it's
more athletic yeah it's more athletic
and it's and they grew the same biceps
you didn't need to go light and and
super slow like an athlete so that's
what I like about being that's funny you
said that cuz my initial Instinct was
that right being on more the athletic
side generally I'm like I know I've been
like this whole don't use momentum thing
I've been against for forever I'm like
no like move learn to move it will
you'll develop and the bodybuilders were
heaving and using momentum back in the
day look at Ronnie Coleman look at these
guys they're and they're not going super
slow negatives um and I don't think
super slow negatives help with muscle
growth either
no but they are very tiring in terms of
like they will suck all your recovery
res it's good to do for variety it's
good to do for maybe maybe it does some
of these things lead to growth initially
but then you don't you just revisit them
but anyway I think Hip thrusts are like
one rep per second at my gym maybe one
and a half say what you want criticize
me all you want but scoreboard let's
look at before and after pictures and I
don't mean to be cocky but like I get
annoyed when look at my girls glute
development do you think we're lacking
and we're doing explosive hip thrust
okay so what I think those initial
studies I got to look at two things
number one were they still sprinting
because if these were athletes and you
have them stop sprinting for eight weeks
then this is a dra Trin this is to see
if hip thrust counteract the effects of
dra trining yeah if they didn't get
faster but they didn't get slower that's
huge hip you can hip thrust and while
you stop sprinting and retain your
Sprint speed yeah that would be cool to
know and speed is as we know is the
first thing to go so not sprinting for
six weeks if this is actually the case
which it may not be that would be
enormous you would expect a significant
loss but also if it's a slow tempo that
does that doesn't have ecological
validity and that's my problem in the
research as in another way of saying
that's not how people do it in the real
world no so and so I'd like so I think
may maybe some of the other studies that
came after that so then you had a couple
studies show that hypos didn't build
Sprint speed and that's when I came out
with my blog post saying I was wrong I
thought I was ahead of the research I
wasn't everyone respected me for that
and now it's years later now there's
actually a lot of evidence that hypos
are better than squats and then but in
general horizontal exercises seem to be
better at developing Sprint speed but
this is interesting because the Plotkin
study showed similar glute growth but
the squat group had more quad and
adductor growth twice the quad and and
over two times two and a half times I
think the adductor growth neither grew
the hamstrings or glut medius Minimus so
you can't tell me in sports quads and
adductors aren't important so I would
never say stop squatting because you
need quads you need adductors you need
glutes but you do need strength through
a full range of motion and squats
probably get you more hip more glute
strength in the hips Flex position hip
thrust in the hips extended position but
there's something about explosive
movements and there's even a study
showing that bands might be more
effective than free weights because you
explode up so I think we need to look in
more into I have a few different glute
in the first room in glute Lab Fort
Lauderdale is our hip thrust room but we
I I have in there a kneeling the glute
Builder has a kneeling glute isolator
it's kneeling hip extension oh yeah
you're bent over you're kneeling and you
do back extension like it's like SX is
back attack machine but kneeling okay
and then you have the reverse glute ham
that's a Rogers piece where you're
laying on your back and there's a pad
and you it's almost like a like looks
like a leg curl Pad but you move it in
hip extension the whole way well when I
do 20 rep set of hip thrust versus the
kneeling glute isolate versus the
reverse glute ham a 20 rep set will take
not not even 30 seconds with the hip
thrust it might be 25 seconds a kneeling
glute isolator might be 35 30 35 and
then reverse glute ham will be 40 to 60
it'll actually be like 60 seconds it's a
long time and so these people talk about
Tempo and they don't consider the range
of motion so you how to tell tell me you
don't know about weight training without
telling me you don't know about weight
training is mention that all exercise
need the same tempo yeah what do people
do with cab raises what about shrugs am
I supposed to do shrugs with two seconds
up 4 seconds down no shrugs are one
second you don't need to so anyway I
think that helps with athleticism is
these rapid like with hip thrust boom
explode up they don't beat you up as
much um they don't cause much muscle
damage they're explosive concentrics you
don't have to control the negative and
you can say the negative is huge is it
for acceleration when you're leaning
forward accelerating is pure concentric
you're not there's not an Ecentric phase
with acceleration sprinting I think
concentric is King and I think you need
to power through the whole stride and
that's why hip thrs are great so you're
also not saying it's the only exercise
to do no hell no you look at what you
look at what of the many what the Sprint
popular Sprint coaches have always dra
what is US ATF or whatever the trk and
field what have they always done
vertical like Olympic squats rdl's
Olympic lifts yep but like Charlie
Francis was thrown in the reverse leg
press yep that's a kickback you know and
um so add in some hip thrust but just
make sure you're not overdoing the
strength training cuz I would become the
coach and I would over prioritize
strength and I'd actually make them
slower I'd make them slower yeah cuz I'd
be obsessed with getting them stronger
at these exercises and really you need
to save your juice for the explosive
stuff the sprinting the plos it's like
you said at the beginning don't forget
the priorities right yes like make sure
that the goal is there you're just
saying that potentially you could
consider adding a horizontal movements
uh if horizontal speed is is the
priority is the goal Okay so real quick
so I so that's the first time I had to
say I was wrong but then I kind of end
up being right anyway I need not to
start to your own criticisms here but
that up then later on with that hip
thrust versus squat study I thought for
sure hip thrust were going to win and
this is what annoyed me term beat out
squats for glute growth y they tied um
they tied for upper middle and lower
glute Max and so then it leads to the
next hypoth is well we equated volume
you don't have to equate volume in the
real world you can handle more volume
what if we would have done more volume
blah blah blah we need more studies but
I was wrong because I thought hip thrust
would beat squats and they tied I it was
on beginners beginners seem to have more
stretch related growth due to sarom
Genesis which tends to stop at around
say six eight weeks whatever but um I
made I did make a post saying I was
wrong well why didn't all the other guys
make posts saying they were wrong too
cuz they all thought squats would
annihilate hip drust I thought hip drust
would beat out squats we were all wrong
but I was the only one to say it um so
anyway that's the secret to answer your
question how do you pivot I guess as new
research comes out you be the first to
announce it and then you change your
programming to reflect that you learn
and you evolve and that's the secret no
one's mad at you in fact they trust you
more but it's really hard for guys to do
it is so hard for guys to say I was
wrong it's it's okay for guys to admit
they were wrong like five years later oh
back in the day we used to think that
squats grew your arms because we'd say
do squats and it you know raises your
testosterone growth hormone your arms
are going to get jacked and now we know
this is a real thing what you're saying
by the way now we know that's not true
the hormon
hypothesis it was probably smart I I
like that we told people that but we
were wrong yeah but yeah we got him to
squat DEA by pretending it was going to
build your arms yeah I used to say that
all the time used say it too um I came
across a document I give out to my first
gym and it was like so pseudo scientific
it was yeah was it was full of pseudo
science but anyway it's fine for guys to
admit they were wrong five years later
10 years later but at the time it's hard
to say guys this study just came out
looks like I was wrong I've been telling
people that and you can say okay I'd
still like to see it in advanced lifters
I would still like to see but it looks
like if you say front squat suck because
you're not building quads you're just
limited by upper body your quads could
keep going but you cave and you f like
and then the study comes out saying
front squats and lead to the same quad
growth as back squats you should tell
your people if you're a scientist you
tell your people if you're a zealot you
don't mention that study you pretend it
never existed if you say hip thrust suck
and a study comes out showing hip thrust
tied squats you need to come out to your
people and say looks like I was wrong
hip thrust there might be more to hip
thrust yeah but either way you should be
saying we should do both I still think
squats are better than hip thrust for
glut or I still think Hip thrusts are
better than squats but as of now we
should probably be doing both especially
since they they kind of combined to to
form comprehensive glute strength
through a full range of motion full
spectrum glute strength and especially
because they don't beat each other up
like one doesn't beat you up as more
one's more full body grows the quas and
addictors too one is more isolation and
guys will look you straight in the face
and say don't do any GL glute isolation
work and I wish women could say oh I
shouldn't do hip thrust no I shouldn't
do Kickbacks no I shouldn't do abduction
no well what do you do for your chest do
you just do
bench oh you do pack deck too what do
you do for your arms do you do curls
because you could just grow them doing
chinups and close grip bench you do
curls and tricep extensions oh what
about your side delts do you do lateral
raises because you could just say just
do just do military press out to the
sides oh you don't even believe so
you're giving me advice you don't follow
yourself you weird hypocrite do you not
realize that you weird man I don't know
why guys do that with glutes but anyway
um that's how you how how how how you
navigate that throughout your career is
you be the first to announce it to your
people you admit it and then they just
like you more because they go this guy's
always going to update us this guy's
always going to give us the science and
then if you disagree with it like fund
your own study look into it you'll just
learn all we can do is learn and grow
from it and then if you're the first
person to point out that hip thrusts
were not needed and I could pivot I'm
still the glute guy I just said hey it
turns out we didn't need to do squats we
just needed to do these e uh throw
electrodes on your glutes and I'd be the
hero because people be we didn't need
exercise but I don't believe that yeah
and then the second part your question
was what are the pitfalls with hip
thrust I do believe when you're an
expert on a topic you should
I could be the number one I could write
the best article to convince you that
hip thrusts are amazing but I could also
write the most convincing article to say
that they're worthless I should know
both sides of the argument I should know
it better than anyone so people will say
takes forever to set up it's a pain in
the butt to set up how did we all used
to set up these stations back in the day
I don't like if I go to a gym I don't
want to do I don't want to set up the
station yeah it is the number one reason
I don't do it literally the number one
reason I'm like loaded device yep if
you've got the Hammer Strength the BC
strength the the Nautilus glute Drive
the booty Builder these are all
different hip thr machines machine even
with a bench nearby it CU sometimes they
put the the bench right near the or
sometimes some gyms are putting benches
right by their platforms so people can
quickly and also matters how strong you
are if there's a bar with one in my gym
it's so easy because I got the BC
strength Thruster setups there's bigger
plates the bar is sitting there with
loaded with 135 you want to add on
plates we got plates with handles on
them so you slide them on you got the
glute lip there to connect it if you
want to do bar plus band you got the pad
on the bar you have a even an ax pad to
sit on if you're shorter and it's all
right there it makes it so much easier I
don't know if people realize what you
said a second ago but you your company
you specifically make weight plates that
are larger in diameter and the reason
you do that is cuz then it makes it much
easier to do hip thrust with you just
slide the bar over when you when you
have big legs and you have standard
plates I got to slide myself underneath
it's a giant and then you go to get in
position you're like and it's crushing
you and you have to kind of like climb
hip thrust I saw you came out with those
Chuck so hard cuz I'm like oh my god of
course you would of course you would
make the first person to change weight
place in 50 years no I got that idea
from markk Bell came up with his Wagon
Wheels oh and so my my um my coaches at
glute lab we hip thrusting off of them
and at that time the best at that time I
was rolling the bar up onto rubber mats
just the 2in rubber mats that I've got
from Elite FTS we'd roll them over the
mats and I'm like the mats aren't
necessary if you have plates that are
two inches bigger in diameter actually
two inches bigger in radius sorry so
yeah we came up with the bigger plates
the the hip thrust station is huge and
and my girls at Fort Lauder they like
the rotisserie station the most the
barbell the standard they like the the
rotating pad the most then it would be
the Thruster Pro which I used the Hammer
Strength model cuz my Hammer Strength
almost got it perfect but why did they
make this tiny plate Peg you only fit
four plates on I've got girls that are
out strong you get a strong man they're
using six seven plates so I made the
plate pegs bigger and then I made the
foot plate bigger to accommodate five
footer is that's something no one does
for women these poor women out there
they finally get a hip thr and these gym
owners are the gym owners are so bad
at knowing what the best equipment to
buy and the manufacturers don't even
test it on a shorter woman who's the
market with right H blue machines yep so
the outside of the criticism of setting
it up in the pain what would be maybe
the next uh pain hip pain oh like the
bar on my head you get super strong I
bruis the hell out of myself there many
times yeah you think I have people would
have the best padding it's hard yeah
it's well I mean you're still putting I
don't care what kind of polyurethane or
whatever material you have foam you're
still going to put several hundred
pounds through that foam yeah so there's
an optimal thickness and density
combination that yep but it's really if
you get it thicker it interferes with
your hip flexion so outside of set up
you get it denser it's it's it it
doesn't Pat as well if you get it too
soft the bar sinks through so the hip
pain and the bruises and the SC and then
it and some people can get bad like my
girls will be like look at this and so
sometimes when you have these crazy
bruises you can either avoid the hip
thrust but sometimes I'll sit on my
client's laps backwards and you do
partner hip thros they hip thrust me and
I'm like I weigh 240 but I'm heavier it
feels heavier I go if you can get me for
20 that's hard so they either hyp me or
they do single leg hip thrust or they do
the kneeling or like some machine that
doesn't put the stress in the exact same
place
okay and then you would say from a
functional standpoint you'll still hear
people say you're lying down it's not
functional those people are dead wrong I
think hip thrust transfer better if you
just said compar it to squats I think
hip thrust transfer better to sprinting
speed um I would the research on
horizontal plyos says they're better for
agility too but I think squats would be
better at agility but I think they're
better for rotational power cuz when you
rotate you're more in full hip EX
exension so I think for rotational power
um hip thrusts are going to be better um
and then they seem to tie for transfer
to the deadlift hip thrust and squats
but I bet you squats build better
strength deadlift strength off the floor
and hip thrusts better probably build
better lockout strengthes as far as just
straight up they transfer the deadlift
similarly they lead to similar
horizontal pressing strength pushing
against a wall as hard as you can which
is a very important Sports uh um
functional performance outcome hip
thrust seem to be better at isometric
mid dipole um due to Joint angle
specificity no doubt Y and um for
jumping they're better for horizontal
jumping broad jumps things like that
broad jumps but then for vertical
jumping they probably tie we think
squats would be better but in the
literature they probably either tie or
maybe a squat slight Edge for squats but
the bottom line is you should be doing
both you should be doing both of them oh
yeah they neither transfer to lumbar
extension strength what else is there
they don't build lumbar extension
specific strength neither one boneal
density any research on that none on
bone mineral density but where would you
do it in the lumbar spine yeah yeah if
that was the case I would think squats
would be better but but uh anyway I
think I think what that shows is for
sports performance you need a variety of
exercises that multiv vectoral training
you know for Force Vector training do
heavy medium and light stuff in your
main directions yes Sagal plane stuff is
going to be Paramount in sports because
yep you know we stand on two feet but
don't be afraid to but anyway so the
functional crowd they're wrong it's
really hard for people to Fathom that an
exercise can transfer like supine
exercise can transfer to sprinting y but
it does then the other arguments would
be
I've heard it all okay it's really bad
for your posture it's going to grow your
waist it's not going to grow your waist
it doesn't activate the obliques much or
the rectus abdominis it's not going to
screw up your posture it's not going to
break your back as long as you you know
well not as long as you just you haven't
actually seen like hardly any back
injuries there's not nearly as many back
injuries but I think the problem I think
why powerlifters don't like it is they
see someone like me doing this weight so
they're like if that guy can hip thrust
then I can and they load up too heavy I
started with 185 back in the day and
worked my way up gradually you got to
start light and get full hip extension
and work your way up gradually and get
that feeling that full glute squeeze and
the full hip extension full hip hyp
extension and so they'll do it and they
don't they're going so heavy they're
only working the bottom ranges and they
don't feel it much they if they would
have went lighter and went full say they
went light like 135 their very first
time and did a pause at the top in full
hip extension and did you know a set of
15 with a 3se second pause at the top
their glutes would have been lit up and
they would be convinced that it works
well but instead they lit up
405 and they did 80% reps where they
failed to get the 20% of full hip
extension didn't lock it out didn't
pause it the top cuz they could never
reach there in the first place and had
antipovic tilt and full spinal extension
trying to mask trying pretend you're
coming up higher but the bar didn't rise
any higher they just altered their torso
to make it look like they went higher
and the back hurts the next day yeah and
then their back hurts it doesn't feel
right they don't even feel their glutes
and like this is stupid why am I even
doing this yeah that it's redundant if
if a study on squats showed that it
built the glutes the same why do it but
what but when would they use that
argument for any other muscle group if
if lateral raises built the side delts
is the same as military press what what
which guy would say don't do laterals
then they'd say do them both yeah if leg
curs and stiff leg deadlifts built one
of the hamstrings the same would they be
okay with that you'd probably they they
do both theyd probably say I bet you
they grow different different port like
the proximal versus distal or different
subdivisions we didn't look at the whole
lot the whole level of muscle the full
length of muscle at every in the in the
semiosis
semimembranosus and then long head of
the bicep fors and short head they
wouldn't they they would be skeptical
but they're quick to throw out glute
isolation movements yeah uh whenever I
think about this topic
um couple things jumped in my mind one
of them is false dichotomy and the other
is mutually exclusive right so when we
think about this um nowhere ever do I
recall you saying things like you should
only ever hip thrust or that the hip
thrust is ultimately always better or
like any of these things so when I say
false psycho what I mean is you don't
have to do a hip thrust or any glute
exercise as your only option and you're
not saying it's the best option um it
it's just looking at research to say is
it actually working and when studies
come out to suggest it works the same or
better or less it depends on the outcome
goal right it depends on what we're
training for and all we're looking you
to put sort of words in your mouth is
what do we know about the quality for
this outcome and there's never a
rational think it is only ever going to
be say a hip thrust versus a squat or
hip thrust versus an RDL or hip thrust
you can do both there's no rule that
says you have to choose squat or this
one right and there's also no rule of
you can't do both at different times it
it's never a ever going to be an answer
of is this exercise better than that one
that's just not how this stuff works it
is simply what do we know that is
positive what do we know that is
potentially limitations how do I put my
person in the best position to likely
succeed as a starting place right
research as you've outlined such far it
only shows us what's most likely to work
most people most of the time y it's just
a starting place from then you have to
coach it's so weird because you've been
to my gym in San Diego y like I have
strong clients they're
impressive I would say we're the
strongest all female natur all natural
all female gym in the
world I wish we could yeah I wish like
there was like some gym in Brazil or
Russia and we tested them we tested them
and they said let's compete because I
could tell my girls up we got called out
we got to compete with them it' be fun
but what would you do strong lifting
which exercise would you do but like
yeah in strongly to the big six I'd love
to I'd love to take on other other gyms
in the world who think they're stronger
than us and and and these girls don't
take stuff they're like I said all
natural and we are so strong at chinups
Ben press military press squats
deadlifts and hip thrust are we as
strong as the best powerlifters no not
at squats and Deads but I got girls
squatting above 315 uh one of the girls
in strong Le comp squatted 405 one
deadlifted
425 405 385 two three girls 385 so we're
not some wimpy gim but it's so weird
though you'll see criticisms of me and
they're like he just gives this girls
hip thrust and bands
and I've never given that because I
don't know the answer so it's always
been yeah kind of that rule of thirds
you know a third from vertical a third
from horizontal a third from lateral
rotary but I do Wonder okay if volume
wasn't equated what if you did just do
hip thrust and
bands and you and you contrasted that to
their programs I bet you you'd get the
same glute growth without quad hamstring
and adductor growth and then you could
could say what's your goal do you want
just glute growth or do you want all of
it yeah and then if you want all of it
probably do the rule thirds if you if
you want more quads then focus more on
you know quad dominant movements if you
want more hams focus more on hinges but
but but yeah like do your squats in a
quad like more upright right do a little
more volume from the squat lunge
category if you want more
hamstrings do more hinge stuff but like
yeah one thing I like about hip thrust
is there it's one of the most well
everyone can do a hip thrust people have
bad anthropometries or poor
anthropometries for squatting and
deadlifting but hip thrust it's a bridge
yep you just put the bar in the middle
of wherever the middle of that bridge is
and the hips and you thrust and you
anyway what you said though you hit the
nail in the head they're all tools and
you know if if you're starting out and
you can only afford you could be 80% as
good of a a a carpenter with these tools
but you want to be the best Carpenter in
the world you want to be the best at
your job you better have a lot of
different specialty tools yep and that's
what I I like having all the machines
all the exercise all the exercise
variations I just told you how we can
still do thr hip thrust when their hips
are hurting when they're bruised up or I
I can tell you when someone's low back
is hurting here's what we do when your
knees are hurting here's what you do if
your inner thighs are too sore here's
what you do we have protocols for
everything if you're this if this gives
you pain try this if you're old and
don't want this then we're going to do
this instead you got to have a lot of
tools yeah and what if you're trying to
grow your glutes without growing your
legs then hip thrust and glute Bridges
because become a lot more friendlier
options so one more question I have for
you why is it so hard to grow the glutes
without targeting the leg
okay because you look at some of the
most effective glute exercise are squats
you know lunges deadlifts they work a
lot of muscle mass so let's think about
the
glutes ideally the knee would stay bent
why because that's going to take the
hamstrings out of it largely when the
knees are bent the hamstrings are
slackened the glutes are going to take
up more of the brunt of hip extension
all right but then when you sink really
deep how are you going to work the
glutes without working the adductors
when you're going super deep you do deep
squat the deeper you go the more
adductors you bring into play um so how
so whenever you go really deep you're
going to work the adductors if you're
doing anything with knee extension
you're also working the quads there's
some evidence that when you carry out
knee and hip exent at the same time the
glutes don't do as much they don't
activate as much because you're
coordinating two things and you're not
focusing on driving the hips forward
maximally you're coordinating those two
actions
um if and so it's like all right
straight leg hip extension is great for
glutes but it also works a lot of
hammies knee extension work is great for
glutes but it works a lot of quads and
adductors and you better do these in the
most glute dominant fashion to work a
little more glutes a little bit less
quads or whatever so just hip extension
alone the what of the hip extensors it's
not just the glutax it's the glutax the
adductors and the hamstrings so anytime
you do hip extension it's those three in
com in combination how do you hone in on
the glutes you could say well why even
do hip extension at all do abduction
does that maximize lower glute growth if
you lean forward and if you start doing
all your volume of Leaning front or
leaning horizontal plane hip abduction
would you develop overuse injuries
probably so you have to look at all
right what about loaded postop pelvic
tilt you just do a glute squeeze that
you feel mostly in the glutes but that's
such a short range of motion is that
going to be effective at growing the
glutes we don't know without hip
external rotation that uses mostly
glutes does it work the upper and lower
glutitis Maximus probably but how do you
create a program around that tough yeah
so in theory you do more hip extent hip
external rotation more posterior pelvic
tilt more uh more leaning forward
abduction abduction in the transverse
plane we have no evidence on these for
growing the glutes we have EMG evidence
showing High EMG activation but they
don't always work you through a full
stretch they don't move move you through
as much Excursion as hip extension
exercises do and so it's complicated
it's tough to just Target glutes without
working the other muscles in the quads
the adductors the hammies and so this is
where glute Bridges become very enticing
and hip thrust and then Kickbacks but
even Kickbacks if you do kneeling
Kickbacks or kickbacks from a high
pulley position you're going to involve
your quads it becomes kind of like a
step up if you straight leg Kickbacks
it's more like a like a back extension
it's like a hinge so you do them swoopy
so they ways to kind of make things more
glute dominant but you'd have to do more
volume because you're not doing the
biggest bang for your buck exercises so
can you do more volume it would be
really fun to do controlled experiment
looking at like the basics versus like a
very grow your glutes without growing
the legs dominant program and look at do
you get the total glute growth doing a
lot more volume for glutes because
they're not as effective but then you
don't get the quad and adductor and
hamstring growth it's not easy to do
you're going to have to get a you're
going to have a lot of bros telling you
you're doing it wrong yeah but it is
complicated because the glutes are
involved in and the the the hip
extension like I said there are other
hip extensors hip abduction you got the
glut medius glut Minimus and tfl um that
do hip abduction as well hip external
rotation you got the hip the Deep six
hip external rotators and so you kind of
create a pro even postor pelvic tilt the
ABS can do it so when you're doing a
glute squeeze you got to make sure it's
not the ABS it's coming from the glutes
so you're not going to be doing the most
popular glute exercise all the squats
and lunges you could throw those in and
just do a couple sets and not do
Progressive overload because you
shouldn't fear getting gigantic quads
from just doing the occasional squat or
lunge you just might not utilize
Progressive overload and you got to do
them in a glute dominant fashion leaning
forward sitting back but it is hard it's
not easy to do and it requires
biomechanical thought and consideration
which I don't see from a lot of people
another criticism of the hip thrust is
just because it looks sexual in nature
so so what I started doing cuz I this on
podcast um by a couple people so what I
started doing is saying I started doing
reaction post to them and I started
saying okay so you're saying like this
looks gay to do but what is a Romanian
deadlift you're doing loaded bending
over so you're saying you'd rather do
loaded bending over as a man than loaded
thrusting personally I think loaded
thrusting is the more manly thing to do
but you're saying so anyway I put it
back in their court and point that out
it's always a funny thing got I'm fine
doing loaded bending over I'm fine doing
loaded opening and closing of your legs
with abduction and adduction and I'm
fine doing loaded thrusting it just
needs to become more common and more
familiar but yeah what it looks like
shouldn't dictate but I get it I do get
it I I I hope we have a little more
maturity with exercise selection than
that when uh when you first got here
today and we were talking I said you
know hey I I don't want to spend that
much time talking about the glutes
and uh well we we did the whole thing uh
but that's okay um there there's your
knowledge is vast in in many other areas
of strength training and you and I love
strength training we could do this for a
very long time very often but one way or
the other we tackled a lot of
information I'll reiterate something I
said earlier although we did focus on
the glutes a lot here I really do hope
people can pull the lessons out to other
forms of training other training goals
you laid a lot of of critical
information about basic things like
paying attention to what the client
actually wants it sounds funny but
that's really what you said you notice
clearly your clients who just happen to
be mostly women were really wanting a
certain thing now maybe other women want
different things it doesn't matter the
point from a coaching perspective was
you really actually listen to what the
client wanted in this case many of them
wanted bigger glutes could be selection
bias there doesn't actually matter it's
specificity it's getting better results
because you're being more specific to
the actual goals and listening to the
client and not worrying about what you
thought was a better exercise because
that exercise worked better for you or
for other clients or a study said that
right it's paying attention um so that
was one thing I I learned about really
thinking about the client goals the
other one was again the examples were
glutes and hip thrust but it doesn't
matter it is making sure if you're not
getting progress that you are truly
progressively overloading that the
effort is there and that you're not
distracting it with either other
exercises or other forms of exercise or
other life things making sure that
there's enough stimulus in the way that
you want to drive adaptation and if
you're not getting it there then you
need to think about other options more
variety more ranges of motion different
range less range of motion like figuring
out what one thing at a time is you need
to change until your goals actually
start or the thing you're trying to
Target starts making progress and then
you gave a ton of technical details um
you covered a lot of biome mechanics you
covered sagittal plane and frontal plane
and we covered a lot of anatomy so
hopefully people that have not had the
exercise science background that you and
I have will have learned a ton of things
again whether they're coaches or
themselves so they can follow along more
with research um to get better
application of their own individual
process and then really at the end there
we finished off with talking about how
how do you understand when new research
comes up implementing changing and
adapting so that you're staying true to
your core your beliefs aren't changing
your principles aren't changing but
you're focused on outcomes not methods
right and methods come methods go what
is the outcome you're really after so a
lot of value hopefully in all those
areas there's probably other summary
points um that I could think of but
those things kept coming back to me
things that people say but you gave so
many direct examples of that from the
scientific literature from physiology
from Anatomy to many many years of
experience that um ultimately that's
just that's invaluable information I
know that you provide a ton of value on
your social media um you do a ton on
your YouTube page and potentially I
don't know if I could spill the beans
but maybe more YouTube stuff is coming
in the near future uh I've actually been
to your seminars before I've seen you
speak a bunch of different times so you
are not shy about giving out information
um I'd love to know where people can you
know learn more about you and all those
things but
you you have everything you have
training programs like booty by Brett U
my wife does it's very very affordable
reasonable good program so that all said
thank you for all that um as much as you
are a a business person and you've got
money to make you have given away so
much stuff over the years at no or very
reasonable price um it you've you've
changed a lot of people's lives not only
have you grown some butts but you've
really educated a lot of people um so
thank you for for all that and and thank
you for my wife cuz she loves your
program so much that said man where can
people uh pay attention to your stuff
and learn it and what is is the best
Avenue yeah it's been
Instagram for the last few years like
that's my main focus like you said I'm
going to start focusing on YouTube
more and then something we should all be
doing is like getting emails so
newsletter we should be better at that
cuz who knows you can't predict these
social media platforms I don't send my
newsletters out enough but I never spam
people so um that's you get it
bre.com um but thank you for the kind
words always happy to come back down the
road and talk about other topics or
updates if we have new science hoping to
collaborate with you on some research
down the road with your new facility
seems amazing and I've watched you rise
up through your we've watched each other
Rise up oh you were way ahead man but we
were like we met through like Barbell
Shrugged podcast and stuff right like
and then seeing seeing you uh become
this uh Rockstar on Andrew huberman's
podcast and seeing you um grow this this
new research position this new professor
position there's no no one who deserves
it more
because I like to think I'm in the same
group we don't just read the research we
work with actual clients and it's
different when you do that you're
looking at
maximizing every athletes
performance on an individual level and
you can't just apply research to the
masses you have to do a lot of testing
and figure out what's going to help them
what are their deficiencies and what are
the strategies going to help them
improve the most and I have so much
respect for you as a practitioner as a
researcher and as a fellow person in
this industry who cares about steering
Us in the right direction so thank you
so much for having me on it's an
honor and I feel very privileged to talk
to have scientific discussions with
someone at your level it's fun for me so
I had a blast man I hope the people
enjoy it yeah thank you so much for
being here thank you for joining today's
discussion with Dr Brett Contreras to
learn more about Brett follow along on
his social media see his products
courses and other relevant items please
check the show notes for direct links
thank you for joining for today's
episode my goal as always is to share
exciting scientific insights that help
you perform at your best if the show
resonates with you and you want to help
ensure this information remains free and
accessible to anyone in the world World
there are a few ways that you can
support first you can subscribe to the
show on YouTube Spotify and apple and on
Apple and Spotify you can leave us up to
a five-star review subscribing and
leaving a review really does help us a
lot also please check out our sponsors
the show would not exist without them
and they're exceptional products and
services finally you can share today's
episode with a friend who you think
would enjoy it if you have any content
questions or suggestions please put
those in the comments section on YouTube
I really do try my best to read them all
and to see what you have to say I use my
Instagram and X profiles also
exclusively for scientific communication
so those are great places to follow
along for more learning my handle is Dr
Andy Galpin on both platforms we also
have an email newsletter that distills
all of our episodes in the most
actionable takeaways we have newsletters
on how to improve Fitness in You2 Max
how to build muscle and strength and
much more to subscribe to the newsletter
just go to perform podcast.com and click
newsletter it's completely free and we
do not share your email with anybody
thank you for listening and never forget
in the famous words of Bill Bowerman if
you have a body you are an athlete